<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ogc-standard xmlns="https://www.metanorma.org/ns/ogc" type="semantic" version="2.0.6">
<bibdata type="standard">
<title language="en" format="text/plain">OGC API - Common - Part 1: Core</title>
<uri type="xml">./document.xml</uri><uri type="pdf">./document.pdf</uri><uri type="doc">./document.doc</uri><docidentifier type="ogc-external">http://www.opengis.net/doc/is/ogcapi-common-1/1.0</docidentifier><docidentifier type="ogc-internal">19-072</docidentifier><docnumber>19-072</docnumber><date type="published"><on>2029-03-30</on></date><date type="issued"><on>2029-03-30</on></date><date type="received"><on>2022-08-08</on></date><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>Ecere Corporation</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>Heazeltech LLC</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>Hexagon</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>Interactive Instruments GmbH</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>U.K. Met Office</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona (CREAF)</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>U.S. Army Geospatial Center</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>U.S. Geological Survey</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>U.S. National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="author"/><organization>
<name>U.S. National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA)</name>
</organization></contributor><contributor><role type="editor"/><person>
<name><completename>Charles Heazel</completename></name>
</person></contributor><contributor><role type="publisher"/><organization>
<name>Open Geospatial Consortium</name>
</organization></contributor><edition>1.0.1</edition><version><draft>3.0</draft></version><language>en</language><script>Latn</script><abstract><p>The OGC has extended their suite of standards to include <link target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource-oriented_architecture">Resource Oriented Architectures</link> and <link target="https://portal.ogc.org/files/?artifact_id=71776&amp;version=1">Web APIs</link>. In the course of developing these standards, some practices proved to be common across multiple OGC Web API standards. These common practices are documented in the OGC API - Common Multi-Part Standard. OGC API - Common standards serve as reusable building-blocks. Standards developers will use these building-blocks in the construction of OGC Web API Standards. The result is a modular suite of coherent API standards which can be adapted by an system designer for the unique requirements of their system.</p>

<p>The purpose of the OGC API - Common - Part 1: Core Standard (API-Core) is to define those fundamental building blocks and requirements which are applicable to all OGC Web API Standards.</p>
</abstract><status><stage>approved</stage></status><copyright><from>2022</from><owner><organization>
<name>Open Geospatial Consortium</name>
</organization></owner></copyright><keyword>ogcdoc</keyword><keyword>OGC document</keyword><keyword>geographic information</keyword><keyword>spatial data</keyword><keyword>API</keyword><keyword>json</keyword><keyword>html</keyword><keyword>OpenAPI</keyword><keyword>REST</keyword><keyword>Common</keyword><ext><doctype>standard</doctype><subdoctype>implementation</subdoctype><editorialgroup><committee>technical</committee></editorialgroup></ext></bibdata>
<boilerplate>
  <copyright-statement>
    <clause>
      <title>Copyright notice</title>

      <p align="center" id="_609a02a1-fa53-7a69-1cb9-ff2ed59292e2">Copyright
        © 2022 Open Geospatial Consortium<br/>
        To obtain additional rights of use, visit
        <link target="http://www.ogc.org/legal/">http://www.ogc.org/legal/</link></p>
    </clause>
    <clause>
      <title>Note</title>
      <p align="left" id="_11e88dba-9912-1a89-a82d-7291bf232191">Attention is drawn to the possibility that some of the elements of this document may be the subject of patent rights. The Open Geospatial Consortium shall not be held responsible for identifying any or all such patent rights.</p>

      <p align="left" id="_15067213-c07b-cba0-7e18-395ab2e00ab3">Recipients of this document are requested to submit, with their comments, notification of any relevant patent claims or other intellectual property rights of which they may be aware that might be infringed by any implementation of the standard set forth in this document, and to provide supporting documentation.</p>
    </clause>
  </copyright-statement>
  <license-statement>
    <clause>
      <title>License Agreement</title>

      <p id="_e8566381-218f-c22d-320d-4d0371bfd58f">Permission is hereby granted by the Open Geospatial
        Consortium, (“Licensor”), free of charge and subject to the terms set
        forth below, to any person obtaining a copy of this Intellectual Property and
        any associated documentation, to deal in the Intellectual Property without
        restriction (except as set forth below), including without limitation the
        rights to implement, use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, and/or
        sublicense copies of the Intellectual Property, and to permit persons to whom
        the Intellectual Property is furnished to do so, provided that all copyright notices
        on the intellectual property are retained intact and that each person to whom
        the Intellectual Property is furnished agrees to the terms of this Agreement.</p>

      <p id="_52ebb386-d365-27d0-d76d-a59ac165fc4d">If you modify the Intellectual Property, all copies of
        the modified Intellectual Property must include, in addition to the above
        copyright notice, a notice that the Intellectual Property includes
        modifications that have not been approved or adopted by LICENSOR.</p>

      <p id="_178f14b4-0718-a5b8-09cd-84f8f4b756ed">THIS LICENSE IS A COPYRIGHT LICENSE ONLY, AND DOES NOT
        CONVEY ANY RIGHTS UNDER ANY PATENTS THAT MAY BE IN FORCE ANYWHERE IN THE WORLD.
        THE INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY IS PROVIDED “AS
        IS”, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT
        LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE,
        AND NONINFRINGEMENT OF THIRD PARTY RIGHTS. THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR HOLDERS
        INCLUDED IN THIS NOTICE DO NOT WARRANT THAT THE FUNCTIONS CONTAINED IN THE
        INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY WILL MEET YOUR REQUIREMENTS OR THAT THE OPERATION OF THE
        INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY WILL BE UNINTERRUPTED OR ERROR FREE. ANY USE OF THE
        INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY SHALL BE MADE ENTIRELY AT THE USER’S OWN RISK. IN NO
        EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR ANY CONTRIBUTOR OF INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY
        RIGHTS TO THE INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, OR ANY DIRECT,
        SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, OR ANY DAMAGES WHATSOEVER RESULTING
        FROM ANY ALLEGED INFRINGEMENT OR ANY LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
        AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR UNDER ANY OTHER LEGAL THEORY, ARISING OUT
        OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE IMPLEMENTATION, USE, COMMERCIALIZATION OR
        PERFORMANCE OF THIS INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY.</p>

      <p id="_2ad7fe27-9ae4-52c5-9dd9-faa4004247fb">This license is effective until terminated. You may
        terminate it at any time by destroying the Intellectual Property together with
        all copies in any form. The license will also terminate if you fail to comply
        with any term or condition of this Agreement. Except as provided in the
        following sentence, no such termination of this license shall require the
        termination of any third party end-user sublicense to the Intellectual Property
        which is in force as of the date of notice of such termination. In addition,
        should the Intellectual Property, or the operation of the Intellectual
        Property, infringe, or in LICENSOR’s sole opinion be
        likely to infringe, any patent, copyright, trademark or other right of a third
        party, you agree that LICENSOR, in its sole discretion, may terminate this
        license without any compensation or liability to you, your licensees or any
        other party. You agree upon termination of any kind to destroy or cause to be
        destroyed the Intellectual Property together with all copies in any form,
        whether held by you or by any third party.</p>

      <p id="_3254c815-179c-5f54-9a01-b8e964837171">Except as contained in this notice, the name of
        LICENSOR or of any other holder of a copyright in all or part of the Intellectual
        Property shall not be used in advertising or otherwise to promote the sale, use
        or other dealings in this Intellectual Property without prior written
        authorization of LICENSOR or such copyright holder. LICENSOR is and shall at
        all times be the sole entity that may authorize you or any third party to use
        certification marks, trademarks or other special designations to indicate
        compliance with any LICENSOR standards or specifications.
        This Agreement is
        governed by the laws of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. The application to
        this Agreement of the United Nations Convention on Contracts for the
        International Sale of Goods is hereby expressly excluded. In the event any
        provision of this Agreement shall be deemed unenforceable, void or invalid, such
        provision shall be modified so as to make it valid and enforceable, and as so
        modified the entire Agreement shall remain in full force and effect. No
        decision, action or inaction by LICENSOR shall be construed to be a waiver of
        any rights or remedies available to it.</p>

      <p id="_4fa1ef5b-3dd5-7a05-3c68-bca93a0f14bb">None of the Intellectual Property or underlying information or technology may be downloaded or otherwise exported or reexported in violation of U.S. export laws and regulations. In addition, you are responsible for complying with any local laws in your jurisdiction which may impact your right to import, export or use the Intellectual Property, and you represent that you have complied with any regulations or registration procedures required by applicable law to make this license enforceable.</p>
    </clause>
  </license-statement>

  <legal-statement>
    
    
    <clause>
      <title>Notice</title>
      <p id="_a156d1c4-313c-340a-8480-366345e3e0d2">This document is an OGC Member approved international standard. This document is available on a royalty free, non-discriminatory basis. Recipients of this document are invited to submit, with their comments, notification of any relevant patent rights of which they are aware and to provide supporting documentation.
      </p>
    </clause>
    


    

  </legal-statement>




  <feedback-statement>
    
    <clause id="boilerplate-standard-feedback">
      <p id="_bbc1a653-f270-135d-9455-af930feb3587">Suggested additions, changes and comments on this document are welcome and encouraged. Such suggestions may be submitted using the online change request form on OGC web site: <link target="http://portal.opengeospatial.org/public_ogc/change_request.php">http://portal.opengeospatial.org/public_ogc/change_request.php</link></p>
    </clause>
    
  </feedback-statement>
</boilerplate>
<preface><abstract id="_abstract"><title>Abstract</title><p id="_5086a340-1d12-4446-7733-e3aa3b07d815">The OGC has extended their suite of standards to include <link target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource-oriented_architecture">Resource Oriented Architectures</link> and <link target="https://portal.ogc.org/files/?artifact_id=71776&amp;version=1">Web APIs</link>. In the course of developing these standards, some practices proved to be common across multiple OGC Web API standards. These common practices are documented in the OGC API — Common Multi-Part Standard. OGC API — Common standards serve as reusable building-blocks. Standards developers will use these building-blocks in the construction of OGC Web API Standards. The result is a modular suite of coherent API standards which can be adapted by an system designer for the unique requirements of their system.</p>

<p id="_1d584693-c450-070d-64a5-859dbeb670ed">The purpose of the OGC API — Common — Part 1: Core Standard (API-Core) is to define those fundamental building blocks and requirements which are applicable to all OGC Web API Standards.</p>
</abstract><foreword id="preface-section" obligation="informative">
<title>Preface</title>
<p id="_8ba0feed-acfd-bc4f-1d13-2e75dab20f9a">Attention is drawn to the possibility that some of the elements of this document may be the subject of patent rights. The Open Geospatial Consortium shall not be held responsible for identifying any or all such patent rights.</p>

<p id="_25f6b7a1-8657-2655-9eff-47df179631e0">Recipients of this document are requested to submit, with their comments, notification of any relevant patent claims or other intellectual property rights of which they may be aware that might be infringed by any implementation of the standard set forth in this document, and to provide supporting documentation.</p>
</foreword><clause id="security-considerations-section" type="security" obligation="informative">
<title>Security considerations</title>
<p id="_6fceaf1b-ef82-3d7c-b807-68f8aab9fe76">The OGC API — Common — Part 1: Core Standard does not specify any specific security controls. However, it was constructed so that security controls can be added without impacting conformance.</p>

<p id="_1725807d-e926-205c-cdf0-07b671017d8f">See <xref target="rc_oas30-security"/> for a discussion of OpenAPI support for security controls.</p>
</clause><submitters id="submitters-section">
<title>Submitters</title>
<p id="_feaa5b51-ad60-39cf-a4bd-25c944916941">All questions regarding this submission should be directed to the editors or the submitters:</p>

<table id="submitters-table" width="90%" unnumbered="true"><colgroup><col width="40%"/><col width="60%"/></colgroup>
<name>Submitters</name>
<thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left"><strong>Name</strong></th>
<th valign="middle" align="left"><strong>Affiliation</strong></th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Charles Heazel <em>(editor)</em></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Heazeltech</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">David Blodgett</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">U.S. Geological Survey</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Clemens Portele</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">interactive instruments GmbH</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Sylvester Hagler</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">U.S. National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Jeffrey Harrison</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">U.S. Army Geospatial Center</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Frédéric Houbie</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Hexagon</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Jérôme Jacovella-St-Louis</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Ecere Corporation</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Chris Little</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">U.K. Met Office</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Joan  Masó</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">UAB-CREAF</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Donald Sullivan</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">NASA</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Panagiotis (Peter) A. Vretanos</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">CubeWerx Inc.</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
</submitters></preface><sections>




<clause id="_scope" type="scope" obligation="normative">
<title>Scope</title>
<p id="_92832b18-b98e-dd72-ca4d-5d93b2f1ad49">The OGC API-Common Part 1 Standard provides the fundamental rules for implementing an OGC Web API. It seeks to establish a solid foundation which can be extended by other resource-specific Web API Standards.</p>

<p id="_d26ef936-9106-2c30-0c31-82f018422984">First, this Standard establishes rules for the use of HTTP protocols and URIs. These requirements seek to provide both API servers and clients a predictable environment for the exchange of HTTP requests and responses. These rules ARE applicable reqardless of the resources being accessed.</p>

<p id="_85f78096-307b-20cc-cc0d-96a6fa136c4a">Then this Standard enables discovery operations directed against a Web API implementation. It identifies the hosted resources, defines conformance classes, and provides both human and machine readable documentation of the API design. The requirements specified in this standard SHOULD be applicable to any Web API implementation.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_conformance" type="conformance" obligation="normative">
<title>Conformance</title>
<p id="_5cb62758-6262-bfc2-b12f-4b0e30dd707f">Conformance with this standard shall be checked using the tests specified in Annex A (normative) of this document. The framework, concepts, and methodology for testing, and the criteria to claim conformance are specified in the OGC Compliance Testing Policies and Procedures and the <link target="https://cite.opengeospatial.org/teamengine/">OGC Compliance Testing web site</link>.</p>

<p id="_a45792fa-0546-3501-c4b9-6c055dbf0d1f">This standard addresses one Standardization Target: <xref target="webapi-definition">Web APIs</xref>.</p>

<p id="_5a5eede3-a4a6-985c-06c9-56f79bc970cc">OGC API — Common — Part 1: Core provides a common foundation for OGC Web API standards. The assumption is that this standard will only be implemented through inclusion in other standards. Therefore, all the relevant abstract tests in Annex A should be included in or referenced by the Abstract Test Suite (ATS) in each standard that implements conformance classes defined in this standard.</p>

<p id="_3771afa3-3e58-1237-64b7-fc6748593c6a">This standard identifies five conformance classes. The conformance classes implemented by an OGC API are advertised through the <tt>/conformance</tt> resource on the implementation instance of the API’s landing page. Each conformance class is defined by one requirements class. The tests in Annex A are organized by Requirements Class. So an implementation of the <em>Core</em> conformance class must pass all tests specified in Annex A for the <em>Core</em> requirements class.</p>

<clause id="_core_requirements_class" obligation="normative">
<title>Core Requirements Class</title>
<p id="_25a4225b-3e33-192f-5856-06aa56f0dbe5">The requirements specified in the <em>Core Requirements Class</em> are applicable to all OGC API standards. They assure consistent use of the HTTP protocols, provide rules for the construction of URIs, and define requirements governing the use and processing of URI query parameters. Through these requirements, OGC API-Common seeks to assure that implementations of OGC API standards will provide a predictable interface for their peers.</p>

<p id="_dc74bebd-3828-dd35-0992-93e25820ce2d">The Core requirements class is specified in <xref target="rc_core-section"/> <strong>Core Requirements Class</strong>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_landing_page_requirements_class" obligation="normative">
<title>Landing Page Requirements Class</title>
<p id="_a3a10997-1d05-1e1b-e98c-9df7e9da6145">The requirements specified in the <em>Landing Page Requirements Class</em> provide a minimal useful service interface for an OGC Web API. These resources convey a basic understanding of the API and provide a starting point for further discovery. The requirements specified in this requirements class are recommended for all OGC Web APIs.</p>

<p id="_1483b33a-4a86-7c06-b7ce-ef4657c999a7">The Landing Page requirements class is specified in <xref target="rc_landing-page-section"/> <strong>Landing Page Requirements Class</strong>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_encoding_requirements_classes" obligation="normative">
<title>Encoding Requirements Classes</title>
<p id="_942b5ef9-3262-eb5e-a760-f8d3d8574bd1">The OGC API — Common Standard does not mandate a specific encoding or format for representations of resources. However, both <em>HTML</em> and <em>JSON</em> are commonly used encodings for spatial data on the web. The <em>HTML</em> and <em>JSON</em> requirements classes specify the encoding of resource representations using:</p>

<ul id="_f7233cb4-1b00-b16b-d9a1-e74cc8fb4bc1"><li><p id="_13ad5f24-ce72-f693-9716-f7b1b26e9213"><xref target="rc_html-section">HTML</xref></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_5d65c306-20ad-4def-d254-399dd30f4710"><xref target="rc_json-section">JSON</xref></p>
</li>
</ul>

<p id="_207525ce-c72b-a83a-8f4c-f1612e6d52ab">Neither of these encodings is mandatory. An implementer of the <em>API-Common</em> standard may decide to implement other encodings instead of, or in addition to, these two.</p>

<p id="_f12dbd19-7bd5-5e8a-a1b6-d9bea39f7179">The Encoding Requirements Classes are specified in <xref target="rc_encoding-section"/> <strong>Encoding Requirements Classes</strong>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_openapi_3_0_requirements_class" obligation="normative">
<title>OpenAPI 3.0 Requirements Class</title>
<p id="_6a930094-dbf9-b132-327f-86cea035a992">The OGC API — Common Standard does not mandate any encoding or format for the formal definition of the API. The preferred option is the OpenAPI 3.0 specification. The <em>OpenAPI 3.0</em> requirements class has been specified for APIs implementing OpenAPI 3.0.</p>

<p id="_e6694855-9a39-64b9-44a1-9000be8aeb90">The OpenAPI 3.0 Requirements Class is specified in <xref target="rc_oas30-section"/> <strong>OpenAPI 3.0 Requirements Class</strong>.</p>
</clause>
</clause>



<terms id="_terms_and_definitions" obligation="normative">
<title>Terms and definitions</title><p id="_7fe04b5b-db41-5d9b-ebe1-463b3a0c16c9">This document uses the terms defined in <link target="https://portal.ogc.org/public_ogc/directives/directives.php">OGC Policy Directive 49</link>, which is based on the ISO/IEC Directives, Part 2, Rules for the structure and drafting of International Standards. In particular, the word “shall” (not “must”) is the verb form used to indicate a requirement to be strictly followed to conform to this document and OGC documents do not use the equivalent phrases in the ISO/IEC Directives, Part 2.</p>
<p id="_e0235fe8-8273-26b4-faeb-a580ad58929f">This document also uses terms defined in the OGC Standard for Modular specifications (<link target="https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=34762">OGC 08-131r3</link>), also known as the ‘ModSpec’. The definitions of terms such as standard, specification, requirement, and conformance test are provided in the ModSpec.</p>
<p id="_1448dc16-8929-d666-6525-0249826c75e3">For the purposes of this document, the following additional terms and definitions apply.</p>

<term id="kebab-case-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Kebab case</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_872c8d34-a84b-2134-f1a5-3f0cd4c841bd">A case style where punctuation is removed and spaces are replaced by single hyphens. All letters are in lower case when used in OGC documentation. (<link target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letter_case">Wikipedia</link>) Example: <tt>kebab-case-style</tt></p></verbal-definition></definition>
 </term>

<term id="landing-page-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Landing Page</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_8bb9e894-1f10-0c94-37f3-d29298b76b71">Any page whose primary purpose is to contain a description of something else. (<link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/urls-in-data/">W3C, URLs in Data Primer</link>)</p></verbal-definition></definition>




 <termnote id="_4d5334c6-b602-784a-43b5-d4b6e4f8bd23"><p id="_25022d48-beaa-5236-0003-b8b733b081da">Note 1 — Landing pages often provide summaries or additional information about the thing that they describe. Examples are landing pages for images on Flickr or videos on YouTube, which are HTML pages that embed the media that they describe and provide access to comments and other metadata about it. Landing pages for documents are often tables of contents or abstracts.</p>
</termnote><termnote id="_19bbdbb0-493c-16b9-e05c-2b2941a23b92"><p id="_e648dd08-22fa-61c9-3a0d-1976584f23a7">Note 2 — A landing page for a Web API serves as the root node of the API Resource tree and provides the information needed to navigate all the resources exposed through the API.</p>
</termnote></term>

<term id="ogc-webapi-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>OGC Web API</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_be9fac65-de77-0095-9575-17d56dc97600">A <xref target="webapi-definition">Web API</xref> that implements one or more <xref target="ctc-definition">Conformance Classes</xref> from an OGC API Standard.</p></verbal-definition></definition>
 </term>

<term id="representation-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Representation</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_b370066d-3238-b27d-8896-7ed796f83fe2">the current or intended state of a <xref target="resource-definition">resource</xref> encoded for exchange between components. (based on <eref type="inline" bibitemid="fielding2000" citeas="[1]">Fielding 2000</eref>)</p></verbal-definition></definition>
 </term>

<term id="resource-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Resource</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_c92ca22c-a025-c833-6a39-f4e2f554e9ab">entity that might be identified (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="iso15836-2" citeas="[7]">Dublin Core Metadata Initiative — DCMI Metadata Terms</eref>)</p></verbal-definition></definition>


 <termnote id="_dc7b3ce7-033e-c792-7da3-b00c49e1e318"><p id="_6a20faac-b105-95f3-739c-e4e63159acd1">The term “resource”, when used in the context of an OGC Web API standard, should be understood to mean a <xref target="web-resource-definition">Web Resource</xref> unless otherwise indicated.</p>
</termnote></term>

<term id="resource-type-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Resource Type</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_afe14bc5-5263-5027-2b55-17cc2fbe1a52">a type of <xref target="resource-definition">resource</xref>.</p></verbal-definition></definition>


 <termnote id="_51b1ce4a-95c3-56a9-14d8-6697914133cd"><p id="_bc4839df-3697-7e69-b9e6-11e96d9e2ee0">Resource types are re-usable components that are independent of where the resource resides in the API.</p>
</termnote></term>

<term id="uri-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_a2e87474-8ac5-d4f0-8323-4b2533fcd28f">an identifier consisting of a sequence of characters matching the syntax rule named “&lt;URI&gt;”. (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">IETF RFC 3986</eref>)</p></verbal-definition></definition>
 </term>

<term id="url-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Uniform Resource Locator (URL)</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_f095ec20-c869-5c94-10b4-ce010a729443">the subset of <xref target="uri-definition">URIs</xref> that, in addition to identifying a resource, provide a means of locating the resource by describing its primary access mechanism (e.g., its network “location”). (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">IETF RFC 3986</eref>)</p></verbal-definition></definition>
 </term>

<term id="webapi-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Web API</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_4c7cd601-7520-5b9c-ddfe-62024abf22cf">API using an architectural style that is founded on the technologies of the Web. (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="DWBP" citeas="[15]">W3C Data on the Web Best Practices</eref>)</p></verbal-definition></definition>
 </term>

<term id="web-resource-definition"><preferred><expression>
<name>Web Resource</name>
</expression>
</preferred>
<definition><verbal-definition><p id="_1602da99-53a6-3b18-27b2-5f2df49ebb99">a <xref target="resource-definition">resource</xref> that is identified by a URI.</p></verbal-definition></definition>
 </term>
</terms>

<definitions id="_abbreviated_terms" type="abbreviated_terms" obligation="normative">
<title>Abbreviated terms</title>
<dl id="_7a12c06c-e59d-c271-3258-c8b0259d6ec5"><dt id="symbol-api">API</dt><dd><p id="_2f15c3f3-297b-787f-6b18-fcd4ed2616dd">Application Programming Interface</p>
</dd>
<dt id="symbol-cors">CORS</dt><dd><p id="_6fe9f3cc-2f4b-1e89-f489-0734f2d99843">Cross-Origin Resource Sharing</p>
</dd>
<dt id="symbol-http">HTTP</dt><dd><p id="_b3c9b82a-8b6c-dbff-0aaf-e968df85b993">Hypertext Transfer Protocol</p>
</dd>
<dt id="symbol-https">HTTPS</dt><dd><p id="_2e14c31a-92b6-506d-9076-8094567a3556">Hypertext Transfer Protocol Secure</p>
</dd>
<dt id="symbol-iana">IANA</dt><dd><p id="_575df4f8-0d92-93cd-0b0b-4c91e779f9ec">Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</p>
</dd>
<dt id="symbol-ogc">OGC</dt><dd><p id="_c62da6ff-88fb-a4db-c7d8-645a88ab5605">Open Geospatial Consortium</p>
</dd>
<dt id="symbol-uri">URI</dt><dd><p id="_d632006f-49ff-2881-6ae7-a5cb628954d5">Uniform Resource Identifier</p>
</dd>
<dt id="symbol-url">URL</dt><dd><p id="_104bf288-5fe2-e326-e64c-971f1b023fca">Uniform Resource Locator</p>
</dd>
<dt id="symbol-yaml">YAML</dt><dd><p id="_a5545da5-5e09-8345-8172-285fccd4998e">YAML Ain’t Markup Language</p>
</dd></dl>
</definitions>
<clause id="_conventions" obligation="normative">
<title>Conventions</title>
<clause id="fundamental-concepts" obligation="normative">
<title>Web API Fundamentals</title>
<p id="_624695bc-9c27-505c-7f49-20af4d833f65">The following concepts are critical to understanding OGC Web API standards.</p>

<ol id="_35d8fbc2-38b4-6723-dea8-07e8fa21288c" type="arabic"><li><p id="_3720bb79-67e7-bca9-2468-aee64aba0540">The purpose of a Web API is to provide a uniform interface to <xref target="resource-definition">resources</xref>.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_767f63da-3685-eb4d-ccfc-37752908fd7c"><xref target="resource-definition">Resources</xref> are uniquely identified using <xref target="uri-definition">Uniform Resource Identifiers</xref> (URI).</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_43b3b2b9-1bab-39f8-f223-9483008dd5cb">A user manipulates a <xref target="resource-definition">resource</xref> through <xref target="representation-definition">representations</xref> of that <xref target="resource-definition">resource</xref>.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_c886c5de-0763-9ef1-47d7-cf56e6e67462">A <xref target="representation-definition">representation</xref> is the current or intended state of a <xref target="resource-definition">resource</xref> encoded for exchange between components.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_699f3c14-9832-3b5c-70ad-bd13419e1a47">The format used to encode a <xref target="representation-definition">representation</xref> is negotiated between the components participating in the exchange.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_306364d3-65a8-0084-7668-2d16ea3466e6"><xref target="representation-definition">Representations</xref> are exchanged between components using the HTTP protocol and the operations (GET, PUT, etc.) that HTTP supports.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</clause>

<clause id="identifier-conventions" obligation="normative">
<title>Identifiers</title>
<p id="_7b794f0d-3844-df24-ec56-8407b18ac0ea">The <eref type="inline" bibitemid="WEBARCH" citeas="[13]">Architecture of the World Wide Web</eref> establishes the URI as the single global identification system for the Web. Therefore, URIs or <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc6570" citeas="RFC 6570">URI Templates</eref> are used in OGC Web API standards to identify key entities in those standards.</p>

<p id="_8aafd94c-6e53-3b1a-e6c4-75c9265a2d0c">In accordance with OGC policy, only the <xref target="url-definition">Uniform Resource Locator (URL)</xref> form of URIs is used.</p>

<p id="_e1baf381-6f03-b9d4-1aca-e552768841f9">The normative provisions in this draft standard are denoted by the URI <tt><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0"/></tt>. All <xref target="requirement-definition">Requirements</xref>, <xref target="requirements-module-definition">Requirements Modules</xref> and <xref target="ctm-definition">Conformance Modules</xref> that appear in this document are denoted by partial URIs that are relative to this base.</p>

<p id="_29cc4a24-dfa4-b0d8-7b59-4aa1fb1d8006"><xref target="resource-definition">Resources</xref> described in this document are denoted by partial URIs that are relative to the <tt>root</tt> node of the API. This node serves as the head of the resource tree exposed through an API. In OpenAPI, the root node is identified by the <tt>url</tt> field of the <link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.3.md#server-object">Server Object</link>. In this document the tag <tt>{root}</tt> designates the root node of a URI.</p>

<p id="_7382e0ba-025d-0827-f4db-deaa161ab475">The partial URIs used to identify <xref target="resource-definition">Resources</xref> in this document are referred to as the resource <tt>path</tt>. The purpose of a resource <tt>path</tt> is to identify the referenced resource <underline>within the context of this standard</underline>. Implementers are encouraged to use these partial URIs in their implementations, thereby providing a common look and feel to OGC APIs.</p>

<p id="_25303eab-eaa2-c13c-96ce-5d0164581ad7">The OGC API — Common — Part 1 Standard defines <xref target="resource-definition">Resources</xref>, which may appear in more than one place in the API. These <xref target="resource-type-definition">Resource Types</xref> are identified by name rather than by URI.</p>

<p id="_e68de12f-566d-f387-276c-fef2a51932f2"><strong>Summary for Developers:</strong></p>

<p id="_2331f1b3-5712-6021-ec43-d0463dfbca22"><eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">RFC 3986</eref> defines a URI in Backus-Naur Form <eref type="inline" bibitemid="bnf-citation" citeas="[9]">(BNF)</eref> as follows:</p>

<sourcecode id="uri-bnf" lang="java">
<name>Backus-Naur Definition of URI</name>
    URI = scheme ":" hier-part [ "?" query ] [ "#" fragment ]

        hier-part     = "//" authority path-abempty
                         / path-absolute
                         / path-rootless
                         / path-empty

        authority     = [ userinfo "@" ] host [ ":" port ]

        path-abempty  = *( "/" segment )

        path-absolute = "/" [ segment-nz *( "/" segment ) ]

        path-rootless = segment-nz *( "/" segment )

        path-empty    = 0&lt;pchar&gt;</sourcecode>


<p id="_09e7360e-297a-0f7d-ab20-31befc1734ed">The following rules should be used when interpreting the BNF for use with this standard:</p>

<ul id="_3c1111da-f3df-906e-8b23-efc81457670b"><li><p id="_349d80dd-5206-32ff-c194-cf80cfb26878"><tt>scheme</tt> is assumed to be <tt>HTTP</tt> or <tt>HTTPS</tt></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_8e16aa7a-8a8b-25b5-7cb1-2716ddcd0408"><tt>authority</tt> is provided by the API developer</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_690a5abf-1389-aacf-5f98-ca10dafe77f8"><tt>{root}</tt> designates the <tt>scheme</tt>, <tt>authority</tt>, and <tt>path</tt> to the root node of the API implementation.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_c986232d-b81d-f428-a292-f7a2118db064">Only the <tt>path-absolute</tt> and <tt>path-rootless</tt> patterns are used</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_ab2a7e07-717e-a547-63bb-bf01745d1b9c">Parameters passed as part of an operation are encoded in the <tt>query</tt>.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_1ea542b7-cdce-d5b7-6640-42684a609b62">Parameters passed in HTTP headers or as cookies are out of scope for this Standard.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p id="_4822ddeb-ec4a-7373-e4b0-265a066e70cc">The following example shows a URI categorized according to RFC 3986 and OGC Web API standards.</p>

<sourcecode id="uri-components" lang="java">
<name>Example URI and Components</name>
URI     https://example.com:8042/myapi/mydata/?name=roads#centerline
        \____/ \_______________/ \__________/ \_________/ \________/
          |           |               |            |           |
3986    scheme     authority         path         query      fragment
        \______________________/ \__________/ \____________________/
                      |               |                 |
OGC                {root}            path            parameters</sourcecode>


<p id="_13a66546-ea7d-7f6c-ca54-4372e60d844b">This document does not restrict the lexical space of URIs used in the API beyond the requirements of the <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">HTTP</eref> and <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">URI Syntax</eref> IETF RFCs. If URIs include reserved characters that are delimiters in the URI subcomponent, these have to be percent-encoded. See Clause 2 of <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">RFC 3986</eref> for details.<note id="_656c3300-719f-84db-caa9-c2cab2a5edc2"><p id="_4bee992e-d591-c72d-ac14-e6ad3e848d8a">OGC Web API standards may include a community-defined identifier as part of a URI (for example: image id or feature id). Definition of the format of those identifiers is out of scope for these standards. Implementers should take care that these identifiers are properly encoded (see <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">RFC 3986</eref>) in the URIs for all hosted resources.</p>
</note></p>



<p id="_4a8e8116-8ec1-1e0f-0de0-4fe5394ef5af">Additional information on this topic is provided in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#identifiers-section">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="link-conventions" obligation="normative">
<title>Links</title>
<p id="_9dae68f0-e6b9-342f-2c27-4dfc0696435e">OGC Web API Standards use <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc8288" citeas="RFC 8288">RFC 8288 (Web Linking)</eref>  to express relationships between resources. Resource representations defined in these standards commonly include a “links” element. A “links” element is an array of individual hyperlink elements. These “links” elements provide a convention for associating related resources.</p>

<p id="_68bfb45e-89e7-754b-5685-4762f999f1f0">The individual hyperlink elements that make up a “links” element are defined using the following <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/link.yaml">Hyperlink Schema</link>.</p>

<sourcecode id="_17571ad6-2cad-4df0-2c06-00ee0ce72ece" lang="JSON">
<name>Link Relation Schema</name>
type: object
required:
  - href
  - rel
properties:
  href:
    type: string
    description: Supplies the URI to a remote resource (or resource fragment).
    example: http://data.example.com/buildings/123
  rel:
    type: string
    description: The type or semantics of the relation.
    example: alternate
  type:
    type: string
    description: A hint indicating what the media type of the result of dereferencing the link should be.
    example: application/geo+json
  hreflang:
    type: string
    description: A hint indicating what the language of the result of dereferencing the link should be.
    example: en
  title:
    type: string
    description: Used to label the destination of a link such that it can be used as a human-readable identifier.
    example: Trierer Strasse 70, 53115 Bonn
  length:
    type: integer</sourcecode>


<note id="_5daa2483-487e-f96e-9cd6-0eb42667a80e"><p id="_789cead6-cf7a-8202-c0c3-7c31889b9b4b">The <tt>href</tt> value is not restricted to absolute links. Relative links are also allowed.</p>
</note>

<p id="_796378ea-6d1d-f4be-2cec-fbf7ff98cfd9">In addition, links should be passed in the response using HTTP link headers. These links are accessible to the client without a need to process the resource.</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core_link-header"> <label>/rec/core/link-header</label><component class="part"><p id="_69e1f5f9-1bf8-999f-8a72-db39767ce412">Links included in the payload of a response SHOULD also be included as <tt>Link</tt> headers in the HTTP response according to <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc8288" citeas="RFC 8288">RFC 8288, Clause 3</eref>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_9ce25fd5-cf24-a4eb-9d99-5bbe61646c2b">This recommendation does not apply when there are a large number of links included in a response or a link is not known when the HTTP headers of the response are created.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>

<p id="_8673045b-87ac-41fb-1fa2-f6563b20d5d0">Additional information on this topic is provided in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#links-section">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="link-relation-conventions" obligation="normative">
<title>Link relations</title>
<p id="_dfbeab7d-5146-5ea2-e1ce-0cbd84dc9f39">Link relation types identify the semantics of a link. For example, a link with the relation type “service-meta” indicates that the current link context has service metadata at the link target.</p>

<p id="_d0bf52b6-d584-506a-955f-bc68172d4eb4">Link relation types are expressed using the “rel” property from the <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/link.yaml">Hyperlink Schema</link>.</p>

<p id="_cb81f3a5-b35a-187e-9468-103f8d23aa09">The “rel” property is populated using values from the <link target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/link-relations/link-relations.xhtml">IANA Link Relations Registry</link> wherever possible. Additional values are registered with the <link target="http://www.opengis.net/def/rel">OGC Link Relation Registry</link>. Additional relation type values can be used if neither of these registers suffice.</p>

<p id="_d0930ec5-469d-8bb4-d7c1-009294ffd897">The link relationships used in API-Common Core are described in <xref target="link-relations-table"/>. Additional relation types may be used if the implementation warrants it.</p>

<table id="link-relations-table" width="90%"><colgroup><col width="25%"/><col width="75%"/></colgroup>
<name>Link Relations</name>
<thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Link Relation</strong></th>
<th valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Purpose</strong></th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt>alternate</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Refers to a substitute for this context [IANA].<br/>
Refers to a representation of the current resource that is encoded using another media type (the media type is specified in the <tt>type</tt> link attribute).</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt><link target="http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data-meta"/></tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Identifies general metadata for the context (dataset or collection) that is primarily intended for consumption by machines.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt><link target="http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance"/></tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Refers to a resource that identifies the specifications that the link’s context conforms to. [OGC]</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt>describedby</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Refers to a resource providing information about the link’s context.[IANA]<br/>
Links to external resources that further describe the subject resource</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt>license</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Refers to a license associated with this context. [IANA]</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt>self</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Conveys an identifier for the link’s context. [IANA]<br/>
A link to another representation of this resource.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt>service-desc</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Identifies service description for the context that is primarily intended for consumption by machines. [IANA]<br/>
API definitions are considered service descriptions.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt>service-doc</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Identifies service documentation for the context that is primarily intended for human consumption. [IANA]</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left"><tt>service-meta</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Identifies general metadata for the context that is primarily intended for consumption by machines. [IANA]</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>

<p id="_9f56bb7b-298b-e4ba-e281-c3fcf9a75c20">Additional information on the use of link relationships is provided in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#link-relations-section">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="https-conventions" obligation="normative">
<title>Use of HTTPS</title>
<p id="_f9b4f5c4-a3f0-7c94-2d6b-1299412d7c08">For simplicity, this OGC Standard only refers to the HTTP protocol. This is not meant to exclude the use of HTTPS. This is simply a shorthand notation for “HTTP or HTTPS”. In fact, most servers are expected to use <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc2818" citeas="RFC 2818">HTTPS</eref> and not <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">HTTP</eref>.</p>

<p id="_e1b7e95d-5569-090d-87f9-ad627136c97f">OGC Web API standards do not prohibit the use of any valid HTTP option. However, implementers should be aware that optional capabilities that are not in common use could be an impediment to interoperability.</p>

<p id="_8ed624e9-b1c4-8124-3336-547a42e99ab1">Additional information on the use of HTTPS to secure API transactions is provided in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#https-section">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="api-definition-conventions" obligation="normative">
<title>API definition</title>
<clause id="_general_remarks" obligation="normative">
<title>General remarks</title>
<p id="_465b8265-92d5-2b72-c527-769aa9b36ed7">This OGC standard specifies requirements and recommendations for the development of APIs that share spatial resources while using a standard way of doing so. In general, APIs will go beyond the requirements and recommendations stated in this standard. They will support additional operations, parameters, and so on that are specific to the API or the software tool used to implement the API.</p>

<p id="_6b751e05-744d-ec0f-21bb-0930502c2e50">So that client developers can more easily learn how to use the API, good documentation is essential. In the best case, documentation would be available both in HTML for human consumption and in a machine readable format that can be processed by software for run-time binding. The used of OpenAPI is one way to provide that machine readable documentation.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_role_of_openapi" obligation="normative">
<title>Role of OpenAPI</title>
<p id="_a3ed70ba-dd25-5588-47a6-30216f4972a0">This OGC API standard uses OpenAPI 3.0 fragments in examples and to formally state requirements. Using OpenAPI 3.0 is not required for implementing an OGC API. Other API definition languages may be used along with, or instead of, OpenAPI. However, any API definition language used should have an associated conformance class advertised through the <tt>/conformance</tt> path.</p>

<p id="_b20b9719-33b9-d746-1d53-4a7c7ab8912e">This standard includes a <xref target="rc_oas30-section">conformance class</xref> for OGC API definitions that follow the <eref type="inline" bibitemid="openapi" citeas="openapi">OpenAPI specification 3.0</eref>. Alternative API definition languages are also allowed. Conformance classes for additional API definition languages will be added as the OGC API landscape continues to evolve.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_references_to_openapi_components_in_normative_statements" obligation="normative">
<title>References to OpenAPI components in normative statements</title>
<p id="_053a2219-de02-331d-0f8d-700c138a36b5">Some normative statements (requirements, recommendations and permissions) use a phrase that a component in the API definition of the server must be “based upon” a schema or parameter component in the OGC schema repository.</p>

<p id="_cd15d87c-5154-9791-d528-22f5afb39e45">In this case, the following changes to the pre-defined OpenAPI component are permitted:</p>

<ul id="_b8758b2b-3cd0-1449-5901-dda5f5ef93cc"><li><p id="_edbe07bc-032d-9363-49c8-b9bc5ed88d99">If the server supports an XML encoding, <tt>xml</tt> properties may be added to the relevant OpenAPI schema components.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_add49db8-592d-d0da-d622-3590bed927bc">The range of values of a parameter or property may be extended (additional values) or constrained (if a subset of all possible values is applicable to the server). An example for a constrained range of values is to explicitly specify the supported values of a string parameter or property using an <em>enum</em>.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_0b19ae15-a084-249e-5ad9-b24e7628f050">Additional properties may be added to the schema definition of a Response Object.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_91d5ce5f-989b-b5b5-ae83-cdd3dd82ca42">Informative text may be changed or added, like comments or description properties.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p id="_ce32dfca-ac2e-6a45-0edd-f383d9610cb6">For OGC API definitions that do not conform to the <eref type="inline" bibitemid="openapi" citeas="openapi">OpenAPI Specification 3.0</eref>, the normative statement should be interpreted in the context of the API definition language used.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_reusable_openapi_components" obligation="normative">
<title>Reusable OpenAPI components</title>
<p id="_cc05f04e-f2a3-4d60-3a18-16cb5b37db73">Reusable components for OpenAPI definitions for an OGC API are referenced from this document. They are available from the OGC Schemas Registry at <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0"/>.</p>

<p id="_4752e157-d67f-7d22-81f7-e6bdeefc52f7">Additional information on the use of OpenAPI as an API definition is provided in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#openapi-section">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="overview" obligation="normative">
<title>Overview</title>
<p id="_4ddbf756-d912-c1de-c5fa-fe4c81726bdc">The OGC API — Common — Part 1: Core Standard defines common requirements and recommendations which are applicable to all OGC Web API Standards.</p>

<clause id="evolution-introduction" obligation="normative">
<title>Evolution from OGC Web Services</title>
<p id="_a9420ea0-8f59-b616-8e2d-7b79a881c6b8">OGC Web Service (OWS) standards implement a Remote-Procedure-Call-over-HTTP architectural style using XML for payloads. This was the state-of-the-art when OGC Web Services (OWS) were originally designed in the late 1990s and early 2000s. However, technology has evolved. New Resource-Oriented APIs provide an alternative to Service-Oriented Web Services. New OGC Web API standards are under development to provide API alternatives to the OWS standards.</p>

<p id="_46a29b88-9a28-ce99-feed-09f75c456f80">The OGC API — Common Standard specifies common modules for defining OGC Web API standards that follow the current Web architecture. In particular, the recommendations as defined in the <eref type="inline" bibitemid="SDWBP" citeas="[16]">W3C/OGC best practices for sharing Spatial Data on the Web</eref> as well as the <eref type="inline" bibitemid="DWBP" citeas="[15]">W3C best practices for sharing Data on the Web</eref>.</p>

<p id="_e3dc4a8b-59b2-242c-e34a-eaebf033bf45">A detailed discussion of OGC Web Services and Web APIs can be found in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#ug-evolution-from-web-services">OGC API Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="modular-API-introduction" obligation="normative">
<title>Modular APIs</title>
<p id="_59e1f476-2e2e-c33a-d7f5-6bd6d2853ef3">A goal of OGC API standards is to provide rapid and easy access to spatial resources. To meet this goal, the needs of both the resource provider and the resource consumer must be considered. The approach specified in this standard is to provide a modular framework of API components. This framework provides a consistent “look and feel” across all OGC APIs. When API servers and clients are built from the same set of modules, the likelihood that they will integrate at run-time is greatly enhanced.</p>

<p id="_58514474-7b47-c337-960c-dc69051cd2c8">The OGC Modular Web API approach has several facets:</p>

<ul id="_627b02bd-7f59-f3e2-09f4-4a2538d24ee1"><li><p id="_0585e724-8d56-cc96-74d6-dfdc7036d245">A common <tt>core</tt> that is recommended for all OGC Web API implementations. This OGC API — Common — Part 1: Core Standard defines this <tt>core</tt> in the <xref target="rc_core-section">Core Requirements Class</xref>.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_0ebe0393-3eb9-9b4e-affe-1dfc81c85dfe">Common descriptive resources which allow clients to learn the purpose and capabilities of an API as well as how they should be used. These resources are defined in the <xref target="rc_landing-page-section">Landing Page Requirements Class</xref>.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_8e300a10-1553-68f4-ab93-f11b6c4d0d28">Clear separation between common requirements and more resource specific capabilities. The OGC API — Common Standard specifies the <em>common</em> requirements that may be relevant to almost anyone who wants to build an API for spatial resources. Resource-specific requirements are addressed in resource-specific OGC standards.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_d8198d8b-7e3e-d690-62b7-d4de55220717">Technologies that change more frequently are decoupled and specified in separate modules (“conformance classes” in OGC terminology). This enables, for example, the use/re-use of new encodings for spatial data or API descriptions.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_d25ff5e9-0c31-3776-14f6-67223fc0c276">Modularization is not just about a single “service”. OGC APIs provide building blocks that can be reused in APIs in general. In other words, a server supporting the OGC-Feature API should not be seen as a standalone service.  Rather, this server should be viewed as a collection of API building blocks that together implement API-Feature capabilities. A corollary of this is that it should be possible to implement an API that simultaneously conforms to conformance classes from the Feature, Coverage, and other current or future OGC Web API standards.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p id="_177e3560-a558-49df-cbce-9fe4622d5ef8">A more detailed discussion of modular APIs can be found in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#modular-api">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="using-api-introduction" obligation="normative">
<title>Using APIs</title>
<p id="_1b664cc2-cc35-e4f4-500d-5b286f673ac5">OGC API Standards are expected to support two different approaches that clients may use when accessing an OGC conformant Web API.</p>

<p id="_b621b63d-e058-893d-f557-d67ff1c7e085">In the first approach, clients are implemented with knowledge about the standard used to build the API and the associated resource types. The clients navigate the resources based on this knowledge and based on the responses provided by the API. The API definition may be used to determine details, e.g., on filter parameters, but this may not be necessary depending on the needs of the client. These are clients that are in general able to use multiple APIs as long as they implement OGC API Standards.</p>

<p id="_76c2c872-9ee7-a2fa-cf91-f61b8a5383ea">The other approach targets developers that are not familiar with OGC API Standards but want to interact with spatial data provided by an API that happens to implement OGC API Standards. In this case the developer will study and use the API definition — typically an OpenAPI document — to understand the API and implement the code to interact with that API. This assumes familiarity with the API definition language and the related tooling, but it should not be necessary to study the OGC API standards.</p>

<p id="_586d9d8e-5b58-f59d-b8a9-6f29d8d1f17f">A more detailed discussion of navigating Web APIs can be found in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#api-navigation">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_core-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Core Requirements Class</title>
<p id="_5335a188-707b-2b4e-d5b3-4b8ff0f72b61">The following requirements and recommendations define protocol-level conventions that should be applicable to all OGC Web APIs.</p>

<requirement id="rc_core" type="class">  <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/core"/></label><subject>Web API</subject><inherit><eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">RFC 7231 (HTTP/1.1)</eref></inherit><inherit><eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc2818" citeas="RFC 2818">RFC 2818 (HTTP over TLS)</eref></inherit><inherit><eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc8288" citeas="RFC 8288">RFC 8288 (Web Linking)</eref></inherit>
</requirement>

<clause id="http-protocol" obligation="normative">
<title>HTTP 1.1</title>
<p id="_74cc9d9f-8c20-b303-9827-6aea277fae36">The standards used for Web APIs are built on the HTTP protocol. Therefore, conformance with HTTP or a closely related protocol is required.</p>

<requirement id="req_core_http"> <label>/req/core/http</label><component class="part"><p id="_585ae79e-e3da-e513-85fa-3f8549d48a67">OGC Web APIs SHALL conform to <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">HTTP 1.1</eref>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_44ed2656-5393-060a-575d-c292050af840">If the API supports HTTPS, then the API SHALL also conform to <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc2818" citeas="RFC 2818">HTTP over TLS</eref>.</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="http-status-codes" obligation="normative">
<title>HTTP Status Codes</title>
<p id="_68aec8cd-37c8-d573-c57b-e71761832e9b"><xref target="status-codes"/> lists the main HTTP status codes that clients should be prepared to receive. This includes support for specific security schemes or URI redirection. In addition, other error situations may occur in the transport layer outside of the server.</p>

<table id="status-codes"><colgroup><col width="15%"/><col width="85%"/></colgroup>
<name>Typical HTTP status codes</name>
<thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center">Status code</th>
<th valign="middle" align="center">Description</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>200</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">A successful request.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>302</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The target resource was found but resides temporarily under a different URI. A 302 response is not evidence that the operation has been successfully completed.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>303</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The server is redirecting the user agent to a different resource. A 303 response is not evidence that the operation has been successfully completed.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>304</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">An entity tag was provided in the request and the resource has not changed since the previous request.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>307</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The target resource resides temporarily under a different URI and the user agent MUST NOT change the request method if it performs an automatic redirection to that URI.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>308</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Indicates that the target resource has been assigned a new permanent URI and any future references to this resource ought to use one of the enclosed URIs.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>400</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The server cannot or will not process the request due to an apparent client error. For example, a query parameter had an incorrect value.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>401</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The request requires user authentication. The response includes a <tt>WWW-Authenticate</tt> header field containing a challenge applicable to the requested resource.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>403</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The server understood the request, but is refusing to fulfill it. While status code <tt>401</tt> indicates missing or bad authentication, status code <tt>403</tt> indicates that authentication is not the issue, but the client is not authorized to perform the requested operation on the resource.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>404</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The requested resource does not exist on the server. For example, a path parameter had an incorrect value.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>405</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The request method is not supported. For example, a POST request was submitted, but the resource only supports GET requests.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>406</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Content negotiation failed. For example, the <tt>Accept</tt> header submitted in the request did not support any of the media types supported by the server for the requested resource.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center"><tt>500</tt></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">An internal error occurred in the server.</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>

<p id="_2e33e9dd-5a37-af10-061c-1f7168ddfb96">The return status codes described in <xref target="status-codes"/> do not cover all possible conditions. See <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">IETF RFC 7231</eref> for a complete list of HTTP status codes.</p>

<recommendation id="per_core_additional-status-codes"> <label>/per/core/additional-status-codes</label><component class="part"><p id="_153a1e86-d471-1f3f-533c-20b2745a29a6">Servers MAY implement additional capabilities provided by the HTTP protocol. Therefore, they MAY return status codes in addition to those listed in <xref target="status-codes"/>.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>

<p id="_4bcb7cbc-f2a7-7a9c-a7d9-38d472c9d9ef">When a server encounters an error in the processing of a request, the server may wish to include information in addition to the status code in the response. Since Web API interactions are often machine-to-machine, a machine-readable report would be preferred. <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7807" citeas="RFC 7807">IETF RFC 7807</eref> addresses this need by providing “Problem Details” response schemas for both JSON and XML.</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core_problem-details"> <label>/rec/core/problem-details</label><component class="part"><p id="_6ee765ad-91dd-42f2-ea0a-68bf98ed1f93">An OGC Web API should include a “Problem Details” report in any error response in accordance with <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7807" citeas="RFC 7807">IETF RFC 7807</eref>.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>
</clause>

<clause id="query-parameter-requirements" obligation="normative">
<title>Query parameters</title>
<clause id="_parameter_names" obligation="normative">
<title>Parameter Names</title>
<requirement id="req_core_query-param-name-unknown"> <label>/req/core/query-param-name-unknown</label><component class="part"><p id="_e5765c7a-dfcd-59aa-9c61-ddb071d20944">The server SHALL return a response with the status code <tt>400</tt> IF</p>
<ol id="_998f0468-c3dc-f373-33b4-0d7a00173907" type="arabic"><li><p id="_3fbb8176-e463-edf9-be3f-5ec129713b6e">the request URI includes a query parameter that is not specified in the API definition</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_6e0d1b32-f54e-0a2d-2fff-3984c87e6ab6">/per/core/query-param-name-specified does not apply, and</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_05648694-7f26-88de-8759-3e9d9dc8be0c">/per/core/query-param-name-tolerance does not apply.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_819fd0d4-4226-877c-d236-6616c6e74387">The criteria for a parameter to be “specified” in the API definition depends on the API definition language used, the complexity of the resources exposed, and the ability of the API server to tolerate errors.</p>

<p id="_47dc2dee-1319-6f8c-9b86-19b5dcfa8862">A service implementer should endeavor to provide as much detail in the server’s API definition as the API definition language allows. However, there is no requirement for the API definition to list every endpoint for which there is a non-404 behavior, for it to list every possible query parameter that might affect the behavior of an endpoint, or for it to list every possible value that each query parameter might accept.</p>

<recommendation id="per_core-query-param-name-specified"> <label>/per/core/query-param-name-specified</label><component class="part"><p id="_4b91dff1-e077-8a30-be45-d8c91a39e5da">The specification of a query parameter in the API definition MAY encompass a <underline>range</underline> of parameter names. Any query parameter that falls within the specified range can be considered “specified” in the API definition.</p>
</component>

<description><p id="_6e94c6d3-e204-cf04-8d89-fae6b803e0e6">Examples of a parameter range include:</p><ul id="_164af1d2-c1ef-9dae-885a-97c2ebe79c73"><li><p id="_7540e0b8-fb50-f199-94e3-61ba1533a7ad">A regular expression that defines the valid parameter names,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_0a74f679-f452-32ab-0af2-0fbf7f2a7bde">A URI Template segment that defines the valid parameter names,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_13745ef2-09f2-f4c1-4756-af9ece95d6fd">An indication that all parameter names are accepted (no parameter validation).</p>
</li>
</ul></description>
</recommendation>

<recommendation id="per_core-query-param-name-tolerance"> <label>/per/core/query-param-name-tolerance</label><component class="part"><p id="_a3cf5fb5-0e1a-3ce6-7576-052cd51c6aa5">Servers MAY display tolerance for requests with incorrect query parameter names. These acts of tolerance include:</p>
<ul id="_ec04ebb8-a97e-9011-32ff-0970dda10213"><li><p id="_9ffdccb3-761b-2d26-c8e2-05c68257943a">Accept alternate capitalizations, spellings, and/or aliases of parameters,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_cf52476f-77f7-a53f-7a88-bd2f089fd0de">Ignore unknown/unrecognized parameters,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_edf9f979-3896-36bf-b7dc-c142bddf8de7">Return a response with a status code of 30x redirecting the client to a more correct version of the request.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_792d37d2-f631-463f-ee6e-d521c53786ee">Servers should not be excessively tolerant. The response a client receives from the server should be a reasonable response for the request submitted.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>
</clause>

<clause id="_parameter_values" obligation="normative">
<title>Parameter Values</title>
<requirement id="req_core_query-param-value-invalid"> <label>/req/core/query-param-value-invalid</label><component class="part"><p id="_7cb81d32-e482-5f15-5b82-f52a15a329b7">The server SHALL respond with a response with the status code <tt>400</tt> IF</p>
<ol id="_ff939ab1-5828-7dd6-7bed-05e77757df3a" type="arabic"><li><p id="_58ab18ae-4cbd-9667-1a31-708f6db4d8e6">the request URI includes a query parameter that has an invalid value and</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_b0d6d01d-17af-70bc-7872-499279e49d9f">/per/core/query-param-value-specified does not apply and</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_974ab3eb-ff9f-837b-6a7c-40cc5139cc7e">/per/core/query-param-value-tolerance does not apply.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_1c6cf62e-0094-23a1-5e30-b0ff77738de8">The criteria for a parameter value to be considered “invalid” varies with the expressiveness of the API definition language used and the ability of the API server to tolerate errors.</p>

<p id="_549e28a6-4e55-2bd7-70b2-9457de6a0ed2">A service implementer should endeavour to provide as much detail in the server’s API definition as the API definition language allows. However, there is no requirement to list every possible value that each query parameter might accept. Rather, the API implementation should include a reasonable degree of error recovery.</p>

<recommendation id="per_core-query-param-value-specified"> <label>/per/core/query-param-value-specified</label><component class="part"><p id="_f7fe2eea-9690-8c8b-920e-65e1ae8298df">The specification of a query parameter in the API definition should include a definition of the valid values for that parameter. Any value that meets that criteria can be considered “specified” in the API definition.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_132e24d6-5165-7491-f921-2800c555c4d3">The API definition language chosen may not be capable of expressing the desired range of values. In that case the server SHOULD provide:</p>
<ol id="_82b4498e-62c6-8453-89c9-f158e16d7214" type="arabic"><li><p id="_fe54eae1-e106-b794-811f-918124287737">A definition of the parameter values that best expresses the intended use of that parameter,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_cb6e752b-1855-b6b2-f921-72b7a1692169">Additional human readable text documenting the actual range of validity.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</recommendation>

<recommendation id="per_core-query-param-value-tolerance"> <label>/per/core/query-param-value-tolerance</label><component class="part"><p id="_92762e2c-c1b3-ef8b-135c-115b6f669453">Servers MAY display tolerance for requests where a parameter has an incorrect value. These acts of tolerance include:</p>
<ul id="_b98e51df-1d23-c705-621c-cb1e5fbfd130"><li><p id="_796949af-c4d4-fa3a-9fd2-793a3fb0826e">substituting default values for invalid ones,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_17661105-c3d9-085f-caa5-f5cd6a65fd81">correcting formatting errors (e.g. convert integers to float).</p>
</li>
</ul>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_d60f772d-649b-f58f-fbd2-968743c43d7b">Servers should not be excessively tolerant. The response a client receives from the server should be a reasonable response for the request submitted.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="web-caching-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Web Caching</title>
<p id="_788312f7-3e0f-8b80-f56e-9807f350e2ae">Entity tags are a mechanism for web cache validation and for supporting conditional requests to reduce network traffic. Entity tags are specified by <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7232" citeas="RFC 7232">HTTP 1.1 (RFC 7232)</eref>.</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core_etag"> <label>/rec/core/etag</label><component class="part"><p id="_b99603df-72f4-6aeb-1fe2-7c406cb8d864">The service SHOULD support entity tags and the associated headers as specified by HTTP 1.1.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>
</clause>

<clause id="cross-origin-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Support for Cross-Origin Requests</title>
<p id="_bfb08d84-a354-7f1c-c8ad-896fd493443d">If the data is located on another host than the webpage (“same-origin policy”), access to data from a HTML page is by default prohibited for security reasons. A typical example is a web-application accessing feature data from multiple distributed datasets.</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core_cross-origin"> <label>/rec/core/cross-origin</label><component class="part"><p id="_00fe4e9e-e1ee-6735-efd0-37b8a264c0b8">If the server is intended to be accessed from a browser, cross-origin requests SHOULD be supported. Note that support can also be added in a proxy layer on top of the server.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>

<p id="_c274cac8-2d54-b53f-a8a0-1ce8bb75b83c">Two common mechanisms to support cross-origin requests are:</p>

<ul id="_3d7991a8-6992-4395-df95-279c963a31bd"><li><p id="_9d6637a5-7dd7-0d77-a82d-d4ecfd0eadb4"><link target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross-origin_resource_sharing">Cross-origin resource sharing (CORS)</link></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_e39ded48-8727-ed1d-92d2-d2551d724726"><link target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSONP">JSONP (JSON with padding)</link></p>
</li>
</ul>
</clause>

<clause id="string-internationalization-section" obligation="normative">
<title>String Internationalization</title>
<p id="_c8b39460-b219-7600-c54a-71264f1b6566">If the server supports representing resources in multiple languages, the usual HTTP content negotiation mechanisms apply. The client states its language preferences in the <tt>Accept-Language</tt> header of a request and the server responds with responses that have linguistic text in the language that best matches the requested languages and the capabilities of the server.</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core-string-internationalization"> <label>/rec/core/string-i18n</label><component class="part"><p id="_faf6151b-790c-ecff-5a4f-6c5bf2f5f7a4">For encodings that support string internationalization, the server SHOULD include information about the language for each string value that includes linguistic text.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>

<p id="_ef847df5-1ca7-d229-adf6-549390227b22">For example, if JSON-LD is used as an encoding, the built-in capabilities to <link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/#string-internationalization">annotate a string with its language</link> should be used.</p>

<p id="_62ce79e5-446a-3603-caea-bd13954d6574">The <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/link.yaml">link object</link> based on <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc8288" citeas="RFC 8288">RFC 8288 (Web Linking)</eref> includes a <tt>hreflang</tt> attribute that can be used to state the language of the referenced resource. This can be used to include links to the same data in, for example, English or French. Just like with <xref target="resource-encoding-section">multiple encodings</xref>, a server that wants to use language-specific links will have to support a mechanism to mint language-specific URIs for resources in order to express links to, for example, the same resource in another language. Again, this document does not mandate any particular approach how such a capability is supported by the server.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="resource-encoding-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Resource Encodings</title>
<p id="_61e449d8-51c5-bc26-80b5-acadf935c2a6">A Web API provides access to <xref target="resource-definition">resources</xref> through <xref target="representation-definition">representations</xref> of those resources. One property of a representation is the format used to encode it for transfer. Components negotiate the encoding format to use through the content negotiation process defined in <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">IETF RFC 7231</eref>.</p>

<p id="_33b2e3bf-bef5-5fde-aacf-991c7edfb32f">Additional content negotiation techniques are allowed, but support is not required of implementations conformant to this Standard.</p>

<p id="_3e7f8497-a99d-a9b3-e4b2-3851c7cf4d90">While this Standard does not specify any mandatory encoding, the following encodings are recommended:</p>

<p id="rec_html">HTML encoding recommendation:</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core_html"> <label>/rec/core/html</label><component class="part"><p id="_5e0f4a7f-13dd-215e-7d4d-125b52fb9e49">To support browsing an API with a web browser and to enable search engines to crawl and index the dataset, implementations SHOULD consider supporting an HTML encoding.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>

<p id="rec_json">JSON encoding recommendation:</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core_json"> <label>/rec/core/json</label><component class="part"><p id="_a9808bbf-2989-a71f-181e-af84bddbc830">To support processing of an API with a web applet, implementations SHOULD consider supporting a JSON encoding.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>

<p id="_9788eccb-fc8e-804f-6cd2-564310304021">Requirement <xref target="req_core_http"><tt>/req/core/http</tt></xref> implies that the encoding of a server response is determined using content negotiation as specified by the HTTP RFC.</p>

<p id="_482a1ac0-74b2-927a-ca80-61c47be4b3d0">The section <xref target="mediatypes-section">Media Types</xref> includes guidance on media types for <xref target="rc_encoding-section">encodings</xref> that are specified in this document.</p>

<p id="_a42cb529-66b4-102c-5e7e-af5f5ba5a6c0">Note that any server that supports multiple encodings will have to support a mechanism to mint encoding-specific URIs for resources in order to express links, such as, to alternate representations of the same resource. This Standard does not mandate any particular approach how this is supported by the server.</p>

<p id="_f29c3df9-9da0-b48d-536b-069380ebaaaa">As clients simply need to dereference the URI of the link, the implementation details and the mechanism how the encoding is included in the URI of the link are not important. Developers interested in the approach of a particular implementation, such as manipulating (“hacking”) URIs in the browser address bar, can study the API Definition document for that server.</p>

<p id="_d1ed1292-17cf-8c3d-3633-52305769cb3c">Two common approaches are to use:</p>

<ul id="_db2846d2-f27a-4d39-15cd-2e297ab8301f"><li><p id="_25fe70de-5721-801c-2465-f828478bb29d">An additional path for each encoding of each resource (this can be expressed, for example, using format specific suffixes like “.html”);</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_3ce59ee2-2043-63b6-0711-c925da471a60">An additional query parameter (for example, “accept” or “f”) that overrides the Accept header of the HTTP request.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</clause>

<clause id="parameter-encoding-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Parameter Encoding</title>
<p id="_8b091120-79d0-acbc-b667-a2965c7e043a">The following sections provide the requirements and guidelines for encoding parameters for use in an OGC Web API request.</p>

<p id="_9587c3d4-0926-b826-112e-b55e79068bbe">OGC Web API requests are issued using a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI). The URI syntax is defined in <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">IETF RFC 3986</eref>. Rules for building URI Templates can be found in <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc6570" citeas="RFC 6570">IETF RFC 6570</eref>.</p>

<p id="_f900d72a-36e5-2e25-46a6-7244fcd780ce">The Backus-Naur Form (BNF) definition of a URI is provided in Annex <xref target="uri-bnf-annex"/>.</p>

<clause id="_capitalization" obligation="normative">
<title>Capitalization</title>
<p id="_0166900b-8698-f37b-c1f5-6c6cd4f86328"><eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">IETF RFC 3986</eref> sections 6.2.2.1 and 2.1 provide the requirements for capitalization in URIs.</p>

<requirement id="req_core_query-param-capitalization"> <label>/req/core/query-param-capitalization</label><component class="part"><p id="_48554098-bbeb-a114-43e1-ea1340770228">Parameter names and values SHALL be case sensitive.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_6d072f16-4aec-eba3-538a-2c65bb170911">IF a parameter name or value includes a percent encoded (escaped) character,<br/>
    THEN<br/>
the upper case hexadecimal digits (“A” through “F”) of that percent encoded character SHALL be equivalent to the lower case digits “a” through “f” respectively.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_b70e81ae-a8aa-5163-2ce5-7b267a7e1425">In order to minimize capitalization issues for implementers of OGC Web API standards:</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core_query-param-capitalization"> <label>/rec/core/query-param-capitalization</label><component class="part"><p id="_7f005c99-24e2-129f-e444-d97e41d926fe">Query parameter names SHOULD be in <xref target="kebab-case-definition">kebab case</xref>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_157db85f-fcdd-2c11-1880-0e98ce0a8601">Query parameter values are usually reflective of the internal structure of the target resource. Unless otherwise specified, these values SHOULD be in <xref target="kebab-case-definition">kebab case</xref>.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>

<p id="_1e251489-32eb-cdf7-fbb2-3dc4c90ccb6e">A Web API may allow filtering on properties of the target resource. In that case, the parameter name would be the name of the resource property. These names are defined by the standards and specifications defining the resource and cannot be constrained by this Standard.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_parameter_value_lists" obligation="normative">
<title>Parameter Value Lists</title>
<p id="_6b9e5f21-6150-d522-5ec1-452d1bf6700c">Parameters may pass more than one value. These lists of parameter values may be passed in two ways.</p>

<ol id="_a081d4c6-78ea-405d-1553-62e53309cb06" type="arabic"><li><p id="_fece7f12-ae5a-a393-a6e6-cb59e63e4e30">Repeated name:value pairs where the parameter name is repeated for each value in the list</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_22832614-8c16-d0ff-d57c-0a15a139b0be">A parameter name followed by a delimited list of values.</p>
</li>
</ol>

<p id="_e730862f-c00e-5f30-73ff-61418cf0dd5c">The following requirements define how to encode a delimited list (case 2) of parameter values. They do not apply if replication (case 1) is used.</p>

<requirement id="req_core_query-param-list-delimiter"> <label>/req/core/query-param-list-delimiter</label><component class="part"><p id="_e6896eea-e99b-9e3b-5cbb-74f905d9f797">Parameters values containing lists SHOULD specify the delimiter to be used in the API definition.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_31a77bc0-15fe-7d14-42ec-497f9ae3d506">The default list item delimiter SHALL be the comma (“,”).</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="req_core_query-param-list-escape"> <label>/req/core/query-param-list-escape</label><component class="part"><p id="_b4dd07b6-af7e-8af4-b42d-250988b44ea3">Any list item values that include a space or comma SHALL escape the space or comma character using the URI encoding rules from <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">IETF RFC 3986</eref></p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="req_core_query-param-list-empty"> <label>/req/core/query-param-list-empty</label><component class="part"><p id="_6544ddac-9771-f7f8-bfb9-07c8f0594765">All empty entries SHALL be represented by the empty string.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_df9163ec-d812-1759-6e55-ccc0f84b0888">Thus, two successive commas indicates an empty item, as does a leading comma or a trailing comma. An empty list can either be interpreted as a list containing no items or as a list containing a single empty item, depending on the context.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_numeric_and_boolean_values" obligation="normative">
<title>Numeric and Boolean Values</title>
<p id="_75698e3b-6d04-93a3-80e0-cb73f030d46a">The Geospatial field is a mathematical discipline. A clear and accurate exchange of mathematical values is essential. The encoding rules in this section standardize the encoding of numeric and Boolean primitives when included in a URI. These rules are based on the computer science basic data types identified by <eref type="inline" bibitemid="k-and-r-1978" citeas="[2]">Kernighan and Ritchie</eref>.</p>

<p id="_583e73aa-7ed6-727b-aab9-a6ca0f8a163a">Boolean values conform to the following requirement.</p>

<requirement id="req_core_query-param-value-boolean"> <label>/req/core/query-param-value-boolean</label><component class="part"><p id="_756b256d-b399-0da0-af46-8b190e29c61d">Boolean values shall be represented by the lowercase strings “true” and “false”, representing Boolean true and false respectively.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_ae5ed371-0539-ace3-b8a8-94a62da0424d">Integer values conform to the following requirement.</p>

<requirement id="req_core_query-param-value-integer"> <label>/req/core/query-param-value-integer</label><component class="part"><p id="_996aae12-4040-d56f-782f-aa86a993a109">Integer values SHALL be represented by a finite-length sequence of decimal digits with an optional leading negative “-” sign. Positive values are assumed if the leading sign is omitted.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_2fdcc7c9-56ae-e6bf-1786-742b90f6424d">Real numbers can be represented using either the decimal or double (exponential) format. The decimal format is typically used except for very large or small values.</p>

<p id="_40169811-15fe-8936-0af2-0488e6010466">Decimal values conform to the following requirement.</p>

<requirement id="req_core_query-param-value-decimal"> <label>/req/core/query-param-value-decimal</label><component class="part"><p id="_c4ddfb29-2712-b538-2b7a-ab0ac894cc77">Decimal values SHALL be represented by a finite-length sequence of decimal digits separated by a period as a decimal indicator.</p>
<ul id="_3a765cfb-fc24-8caa-9715-2bd9e047dbe0"><li><p id="_035a5aef-7355-a2da-bd5a-68caa7c9f5ef">An optional leading negative sign (“-”) is allowed.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_5078babd-531e-b2de-b711-98ca2ada3f1e">If the sign is omitted, positive (“+”) is assumed.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_4aeee5c5-e3e6-ac8f-ceb4-d5a913528ba1">Leading and trailing zeroes are optional.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_f3c093cb-970e-9406-2093-6be36c110922">If the fractional part is zero, the period and following zero(es) can be omitted.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_f29ee0ae-5039-12f7-b30d-dccf029e57d0">Double values conform to the following requirement.</p>

<requirement id="req_core_query-param-value-double"> <label>/req/core/query-param-value-double</label><component class="part"><p id="_42847539-947f-9a45-f27f-00bfcc0e3172">Double values SHALL be represented by a mantissa followed, optionally, by the character “e”, followed by an exponent.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_c528330e-8ead-ff3a-d7c3-f3644b9a4c9d">The exponent SHALL be an integer.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_1eb66dd4-c6a2-0b71-7c1d-0b50b49d5ab1">The mantissa SHALL be a decimal number.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_d67e350d-7e95-acfe-e119-a6af66e7317f">The representations for exponent and mantissa SHALL follow the lexical rules for integer and decimal.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_cdae96a2-5cab-e282-f9ec-fba932d320a9">If the “e” and the following exponent are omitted, an exponent value of 0 SHALL be assumed.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_215c104d-fdce-18fa-6145-1ac33ced3e3a">Special values, if supported, should conform to the following recommendation.</p>

<recommendation id="rec_core_query-param-value-special"> <label>/rec/core/query-param-value-special</label><component class="part"><p id="_31e756ce-61c4-509f-0cbc-15969f9de348">The special values positive and negative infinity and not-a-number SHOULD be represented using the strings <tt>inf</tt>, <tt>-inf</tt> and <tt>nan</tt>, respectively.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>
</clause>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_landing-page-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Landing Page Requirements Class</title>
<requirement id="rc_landing-page" type="class">  <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/landing-page"/></label><subject>Web API</subject>
</requirement>

<p id="_bc7ff3e0-c341-663e-7dba-9f0a8398c2ec">The Landing Page Requirements Class of the API-Common Core Standard describes how the <tt>Landing Page</tt> and its associated resources are accessed through an OGC conformant Web API.</p>

<p id="_58b7b1cb-7649-1acd-df39-74f2409fe6b6">The Landing Page resources are introduced in <xref target="lp-resources-table"/>. The requirements and recommendations applicable to these resources are provided in the sections below.</p>

<table id="lp-resources-table"><colgroup><col width="35.2941%"/><col width="17.647%"/><col width="47.0589%"/></colgroup>
<name>Landing Page Resources</name>
<thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center">Resource</th>
<th valign="middle" align="center">HTTP Method</th>
<th valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Description</strong></th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Landing Page</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center">GET</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">the <xref target="landing-page">landing page</xref></td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">API Definition</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center">GET</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">the <xref target="api-definition">API Definition</xref> document for this API</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Conformance Declaration</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center">GET</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">the <xref target="conformance-classes">conformance</xref> information for this API</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>

<clause id="landing-page" obligation="normative">
<title>API landing page</title>
<p id="_2813b5aa-7ab8-4931-9417-ffd0491e3a2a">An OGC Web API has a single landing page on the <tt>{root}</tt> node.</p>

<p id="_45196c0e-e8a8-ca96-5696-a0060d498698">The purpose of the landing page is to provide clients with a starting point for using the API. Any resource exposed through an API can be accessed by following paths or links starting from the landing page.</p>

<p id="_ce8f91c7-a615-b9ab-954c-2ad554a0f28b">The landing page includes three metadata elements: title, description, and attribution. These three elements describe the API as a whole. Clients can expect to encounter metadata that is more resource-specific as they follow links and paths from the landing page.</p>

<p id="_5fa712f5-5447-f4f9-4c1d-138201b101b1">While the three metadata elements are defined as text strings, the attribution element is special. Specifically, the attribution element can contain markup text. Markup allows a text string to import images and format text. The capabilities are only limited by the markup language used. See the example <xref target="json-landing-page">landing page</xref> for an example of the use of markup in the attribution element.</p>

<clause id="_operation" obligation="normative">
<title>Operation</title>
<requirement id="req_landing-page_root-op"> <label>/req/landing-page/root-op</label><component class="part"><p id="_6fb8dd73-5b9d-ed6a-7d7f-69a66a8020aa">The server SHALL support the HTTP GET operation on the URI <tt>{root}/</tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_087c23de-0d34-1839-2464-e428c79f9400">The response to the HTTP GET request issued in <tt>A</tt> SHALL satisfy requirement <xref target="req_landing-page_root-success">/req/landing-page/root-success</xref>.</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="_response" obligation="normative">
<title>Response</title>
<requirement id="req_landing-page_root-success"> <label>/req/landing-page/root-success</label><component class="part"><p id="_3f9c8820-ac63-9203-f768-a14723ecc514">A successful execution of the operation SHALL be reported as a response with an HTTP status code <tt>200</tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_b08a7693-7aaf-7d12-0fae-fb28d38b7e17">The content of that response SHALL be based upon the schema <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/landingPage.yaml">landingPage.yaml</link> and include links to the following resources:</p>
<ul id="_b6c47d85-e090-0778-3a95-2b8ed9631cd1"><li><p id="_282a996e-ffe5-8e58-5cd2-104c670d56ae">API Definition (relation type ‘service-desc’ or ‘service-doc’)</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_66e188ee-2ac8-d985-e7f4-b1da46da0d6c">Conformance Declaration (relation type ‘http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance’)</p>
</li>
</ul>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_8c3c4d5e-afe5-37c9-6a63-138a551b3844">The Landing Page returned by this operation is based on the following OpenAPI schema.</p>

<sourcecode id="_2bdfb20e-0616-a309-96c8-98279d9d7290" lang="YAML">
<name>Landing Page Schema</name>
type: object
required:
  - links
properties:
  title:
    type: string
    title: The title of the API.
    description: While a title is not required, implementers are strongly advised to include one.
    example: Buildings in Bonn
  description:
    type: string
    example: Access to data about buildings in the city of Bonn via a Web API that conforms to the OGC API Common specification.
  attribution:
    type: string
    title: attribution for the API
    description: The `attribution` should be short and intended for presentation to a user, for example, in a corner of a map. Parts of the text can be links to other resources if additional information is needed. The string can include HTML markup.
  links:
    type: array
    items:
      $ref: link.yaml</sourcecode>


<p id="_3eb8af13-b86e-fa81-85a7-9f3e507b213e">In addition to the required resources, links to additional resources may be included in the Landing Page.</p>

<p id="_111bb450-58df-bcfa-d28a-25181b2f5e2e">Examples of OGC landing pages are provided in <xref target="landing-page-examples"/>.</p>

<p id="_a6869c4a-0113-9259-220f-1d28b5bc6538">A JSON schema for the Landing Page resource can be found on the <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/landingPage.yaml">OGC Schema Repository</link>.</p>

<p id="_7b24c717-c4c6-8d38-fc8e-4ae31f82a8be">Additional information about the Landing Page can be found in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#landing-page-section">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_error_situations" obligation="normative">
<title>Error Situations</title>
<p id="_440de991-e79c-630a-8a83-0c0bb9499ec0">See <xref target="http-status-codes"/> for general guidance.</p>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="api-definition" obligation="normative">
<title>API Definition</title>
<p id="_624010e7-fcbf-62b9-919a-35bce2b0b3f3">Every API implementation should provide an API Definition resource that describes the capabilities provided by that API. This resource can be used by client developers to understand the supported services, by software clients to connect to the server, and by development tools to support the implementation of servers and clients.</p>

<clause id="_operation_2" obligation="normative">
<title>Operation</title>
<requirement id="req_landing-page_api-definition-op"> <label>/req/landing-page/api-definition-op</label><component class="part"><p id="_a533cde1-a0c9-8ea8-82f1-083980ee8b13">The server SHALL support the HTTP GET operation on all links from the landing page that have the relation type <tt>service-desc</tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_d9807a86-1293-714a-9640-c8b357d55711">The server SHALL support the HTTP GET operation on all links from the landing page that have the relation type <tt>service-doc</tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_7ae97b9b-02f1-ca69-aade-2c80c9f564c6">The responses to all HTTP GET requests issued in <tt>A</tt> and <tt>B</tt> SHALL satisfy requirement <xref target="req_landing-page_api-definition-success">/req/landing-page/api-definition-success</xref>.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<recommendation id="rec_landing-page_api-definition-op"> <label>/rec/landing-page/api-definition-op</label><component class="part"><p id="_8a679967-88ec-8e67-2163-4f166b0dc278">The server SHOULD support the HTTP GET operation on the URI
<tt>{root}/api</tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_49e5d4fd-f76f-1e91-c9fe-03f6cb8d6629">The response to the HTTP GET request issued in <tt>A</tt> SHOULD satisfy requirement <xref target="req_landing-page_api-definition-success">/req/landing-page/api-definition-success</xref>.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>
</clause>

<clause id="_response_2" obligation="normative">
<title>Response</title>
<requirement id="req_landing-page_api-definition-success"> <label>/req/landing-page/api-definition-success</label><component class="part"><p id="_e1736835-b877-ee3f-cdae-f293135c6f91">A successful execution of the operation SHALL be reported as a response with a HTTP status code <tt>200</tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_04ca1080-3648-5ab1-5b54-263874db32f6">The content of that response SHALL be an API Definition document.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_0b54712c-c9d7-11fe-1a57-9cbca2753537">The API Definition document SHALL be consistent with the media type identified through HTTP content negotiation.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<note id="_8bf6e0aa-e101-131e-2d86-202632c120c3"><p id="_d0d08997-c8d2-0a6f-21d2-959b7cefb236">The <tt>-f</tt> parameter MAY be used to satisfy this requirement.</p>
</note>

<recommendation id="rec_landing-page_api-definition-oas"> <label>/rec/landing-page/api-definition-oas</label><component class="part"><p id="_48f33ea4-8418-20df-1ebd-00ea844814fd">If the API definition document uses the OpenAPI Specification 3.0,<br/>
    THEN<br/>
The document SHOULD conform to the <xref target="rc_oas30-section">OpenAPI Specification 3.0 requirements class</xref>.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>
</clause>

<clause id="_error_situations_2" obligation="normative">
<title>Error Situations</title>
<p id="_3c110932-9c29-a4e1-05e5-5ade40c2be7e">See <xref target="http-status-codes"/> for general guidance.</p>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="conformance-classes" obligation="normative">
<title>Declaration of Conformance Classes</title>
<p id="_b612f45a-ba7a-c346-7dbf-4bd319c0144d">The OGC Web API Standards define a collection of modules that can be assembled into a Web API. The first question a client will ask when accessing one of these APIs is “what are you?” In other words, what modules were used to create you? Since implementers have a choice on the modules to use, there is no simple answer. The best that can be done is to provide a list of the modules implemented, a declaration of the Conformance Classes.</p>

<p id="_d8ee6b22-1508-01d2-7284-66d21effa700">The list of Conformance Classes is key to understanding and using an OGC Web API. So it is important that they are easy to access. A simple GET using an easily constructed URI is all that should be required. Therefore, the path to the Conformance Declaration is fixed.</p>

<p id="_fcf79388-3087-86df-9498-ca755f3b84e1">Ease of access is also supported by the structure of the Conformance Declaration resource. It is a simple list of URIs. This is a structure that requires almost no parsing and little interpretation and is designed to be accessible to even the simplest client.</p>

<clause id="_operation_3" obligation="normative">
<title>Operation</title>
<requirement id="req_landing-page_conformance-op"> <label>/req/landing-page/conformance-op</label><component class="part"><p id="_9e2f34e3-24d2-3cfe-5f35-fe9461ad398a">The server SHALL support the HTTP GET operation on the URI <tt>{root}/conformance</tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_16ae710a-2ff6-08ab-e4d6-481e3440b7e9">The server SHALL support the HTTP GET operation on all links from the landing page that have the relation type <tt><link target="http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance"/></tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_6722da7d-7b08-a4a0-fa09-5f83e422a1c7">The responses to all HTTP GET requests issued in <tt>A</tt> and <tt>B</tt> SHALL satisfy requirement <xref target="req_landing-page_conformance-success">/req/landing-page/conformance-success</xref>.</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="_response_3" obligation="normative">
<title>Response</title>
<requirement id="req_landing-page_conformance-success"> <label>/req/landing-page/conformance-success</label><component class="part"><p id="_f4f4e1fb-d207-aef7-2d4c-f1233a156340">A successful execution of the operation SHALL be reported as a response with a HTTP status code <tt>200</tt>.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_1419e71c-6dac-65d3-46f1-8caead08cafb">The content of that response SHALL be based upon the schema <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/confClasses.yaml">confClasses.yaml</link> and list all OGC API conformance classes that the API conforms to.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_979c5dd7-ee8e-773d-aa1e-55a3b78ec748">The Conformance Declaration returned by this operation is based on the following OpenAPI schema.</p>

<sourcecode id="_bdcc9ca4-1d2b-dd16-ca56-94bddb13d0ab" lang="YAML">
<name>Conformance Declaration Schema</name>
type: object
required:
  - conformsTo
properties:
  conformsTo:
    type: array
    items:
      type: string
      example: "http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/conf/core"</sourcecode>


<p id="_e1d05323-fe44-f765-68c5-15e523643151">A JSON schema for the Landing Page resource can be found on the <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/confClasses.yaml">OGC Schema Repository</link>.</p>

<p id="_904ba0a6-14dd-6200-8051-5e2e509fe936">Examples of OGC Conformance Declarations are provided in <xref target="conformance-response-examples"/>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_error_situations_3" obligation="normative">
<title>Error situations</title>
<p id="_764634ca-c2c6-1631-f394-d0676456f59c">See <xref target="http-status-codes"/> for general guidance.</p>
</clause>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_encoding-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Encoding Requirements Classes</title>
<clause id="_overview" obligation="normative">
<title>Overview</title>
<p id="_ed58de64-9f50-66dd-2605-20ff351f6af0">This clause specifies two requirements classes for encodings that may be used by an OGC Web API implementation. These encodings are commonly used for spatial data on the web applications:</p>

<ul id="_f6f14234-e95d-3a79-de3f-ea6bc5811661"><li><p id="_cc186987-d77e-2005-b942-dd5d15b27694"><xref target="rc_html-section">HTML</xref></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_0ad1b964-e338-8325-7138-6682860e5881"><xref target="rc_json-section">JSON</xref></p>
</li>
</ul>

<p id="_50a07aec-6d4c-3457-6f09-ab5af14f118c">Neither of these encodings are mandatory. An implementation of the OGC API — Common Standard may implement one, both, or none of them. Other encodings are possible.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_html-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Requirement Class “HTML”</title>
<p id="_c79098c8-45ea-8f26-e790-bca0f2839ad0">Geographic information that is only accessible in formats such as GeoJSON or GML have two issues when web application principles are considered:</p>

<ul id="_198f747d-ac73-a81e-3fba-e1a3a7d44000"><li><p id="_97e74ffb-dd2f-b4cd-c60e-fade14232457">The data are not discoverable using Web crawlers and search engines,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_afb84c9f-db78-006b-f154-46f7b2c044ab">The data can not be viewed directly in a browser — additional tools are required to view the data.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p id="_4e3d2737-cb4a-bbd2-a2e3-746218d3a040">Therefore, sharing data on the Web should include publication in HTML. To be consistent with the Web, this publication should be done in a way that enables users and search engines to discover and access all of the data.</p>

<p id="_984c6e59-7129-6073-dfa9-325f4477ea2f">This is discussed in detail in the  <eref type="inline" bibitemid="SDWBP" citeas="[16]">W3C/OGC SDW Best Practice</eref>. Therefore, the OGC API — Common Standard <xref target="rec_html">recommends</xref> supporting HTML as an encoding.</p>

<requirement id="rc_html" type="class">  <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/html"/></label><subject>Web API</subject><inherit><xref target="rc_landing-page">Landing Page Requirements Class</xref></inherit><inherit><eref type="inline" bibitemid="html5" citeas="[17]">HTML5</eref></inherit><inherit><eref type="inline" bibitemid="schema_org" citeas="[12]">Schema.org</eref></inherit>
</requirement>

<requirement id="req_html_definition"> <label>/req/html/definition</label><component class="part"><p id="_d9160921-e841-a234-0196-e214145e12bf"><tt>200</tt>-responses of the server SHALL support the <tt>text/html</tt> media type for the <xref target="landing-page">Landing Page</xref> and <xref target="conformance-classes">Conformance</xref> resources.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="req_html_content"> <label>/req/html/content</label><component class="part"><p id="_6f88d146-cc34-0405-6437-5c5f425ae25f">Every <tt>200</tt>-response of the API with the media type “text/html” SHALL be a <link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/html5/">HTML 5 document</link> that includes the following information in the HTML body:</p>
<ul id="_c9b60e8e-5cf4-856b-79f9-53b8a98ad8d4"><li><p id="_3abe4af2-ec97-872c-16eb-89e80af94ff3">All information identified in the schemas of the
<link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.3.md#responseObject">Response Object</link> in the HTML <tt>&lt;body/&gt;</tt>, and</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_7c65a7ea-f2ca-55fa-fde4-f6d68c051ad1">All links in HTML <tt>&lt;a/&gt;</tt> elements in the HTML <tt>&lt;body/&gt;</tt>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</component>
</requirement>

<recommendation id="rec_html_schema-org"> <label>/rec/html/schema-org</label><component class="part"><p id="_a4878ba4-b38a-0f90-2a77-a786a98b80e7">A <tt>200</tt>-response with the media type <tt>text/html</tt>, SHOULD include <eref type="inline" bibitemid="schema_org" citeas="[12]">Schema.org</eref> annotations.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_json-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Requirement Class “JSON”</title>
<p id="_020943e5-43a4-a84a-7bd6-0c2dfcde9b19">JSON is a lightweight data-interchange format desiged to facilitate structured data interchange between applications. JSON is commonly used for Web-based software-to-software interchanges. Most Web developers are comfortable with using a JSON-based format. Therefore support for JSON is recommended for machine-to-machine interactions.</p>

<requirement id="rc_json" type="class">  <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/json"/></label><subject>Web API</subject><inherit><xref target="rc_landing-page">Landing Page Requirements Class</xref></inherit><inherit><eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc8259" citeas="RFC 8259">IETF RFC 8259: The JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) Data Interchange Format</eref></inherit><inherit><eref type="inline" bibitemid="jschema" citeas="[8]">JSON Schema</eref></inherit>
</requirement>

<requirement id="req_json_definition"> <label>/req/json/definition</label><component class="part"><p id="_236e9f90-3550-bf6f-3b36-50613fd15eee"><tt>200</tt>-responses of the server SHALL support the <tt>application/json</tt> media type for the <xref target="landing-page">Landing Page</xref> and <xref target="conformance-classes">Conformance</xref> resources.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="req_json_content"> <label>/req/json/content</label><component class="part"><p id="_9cefc619-fb88-369e-96ef-0bd9578510a4">Every request to a <xref target="landing-page">Landing Page</xref> or <xref target="conformance-classes">Conformance</xref> resource which:</p>
<ol id="_8d68ad3d-6cc8-ae98-65e2-6c84eb03fe7c" type="arabic"><li><p id="_bc89e6b1-09b5-35ed-7b1b-818248d90918">Receives a <tt>200</tt>-response</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_6310162d-cf1c-1c10-432d-2bd4db19a70b">with the <tt>Content-Type</tt> header set to <tt>application/json</tt></p>
<p id="_6fb4210d-ebc6-2c5a-1b07-0f95c46bd99a">SHALL include, or link to, a payload encoded according to the  <link target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8259">JSON Interchange Format</link></p>
</li>
</ol>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_709e85fa-07b3-964f-112a-34e678d7201f">The payload for these responses SHALL conform with the JSON Schema specified for the resource in the <xref target="rc_landing-page">Landing Page</xref> Requirements Class.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<recommendation id="rec_json_problem-details"> <label>/rec/json/problem-details</label><component class="part"><p id="_3e0183ca-6e9c-5d39-858b-23c6e16da506">Any OGC Web API implementation instance returning an RFC 7807 “Problem Details” report in JSON should set the <tt>Content-Type</tt> header to “application/problem+json” and structure the report using the JSON Schema <link target="https://github.com/opengeospatial/ogcapi-common/blob/master/core/openapi/schemas/exception.json">here</link>.</p>
</component>
</recommendation>

<p id="_4dc3ccb6-fe10-88b4-b42a-1ca9bd16cbcb">An example JSON Schema for the landing page is available at <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/landingPage.yaml">landingPage.yaml</link>.</p>

<p id="_a001fbb5-00e7-a2c0-26d0-7eec1e2496bb">An example JSON Problem Details report is available at <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/examples/ExceptionExample.yaml">ExceptionExample.yaml</link>.</p>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_oas30-section" obligation="normative">
<title>OpenAPI 3.0 Requirements Class</title>
<clause id="_basic_requirements" obligation="normative">
<title>Basic requirements</title>
<p id="_17dee1ed-7d62-29ae-5187-39a78ccae339">APIs conforming to this requirements class are self documenting using an <link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.3.md#oasDocument">OpenAPI Document</link>.</p>

<requirement id="rc_oas30" type="class">  <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/oas30"/></label><subject>Web API</subject><inherit><eref type="inline" bibitemid="openapi" citeas="openapi">OpenAPI Specification 3.0</eref></inherit>
</requirement>

<requirement id="req_oas30_oas-definition-1"> <label>/req/oas30/oas-definition-1</label><component class="part"><p id="_916fc153-4316-4fa6-c51a-9a253c5304a9">An OpenAPI definition in JSON using the media type <tt>application/vnd.oai.openapi+json;version=3.0</tt> and a HTML version of the API definition using the media type <tt>text/html</tt> SHALL be available.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="req_oas30_oas-definition-2"> <label>/req/oas30/oas-definition-2</label><component class="part"><p id="_48babc53-510b-a0e2-e472-1ed54b360850">The JSON representation SHALL conform to the <eref type="inline" bibitemid="openapi" citeas="openapi">OpenAPI Specification, version 3.0</eref>.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_4ae0ebb7-a995-93ab-6746-d896bc7b1e8e">Two example OpenAPI documents are included in <xref target="oas-examples">Annex B</xref>.</p>

<requirement id="req_oas30_oas-impl"> <label>/req/oas30/oas-impl</label><component class="part"><p id="_cbac0344-8e19-a702-4efd-879c0004b19b">The API SHALL implement all capabilities specified in the OpenAPI definition.</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="_complete_definition" obligation="normative">
<title>Complete definition</title>
<requirement id="req_oas30_completeness"> <label>/req/oas30/completeness</label><component class="part"><p id="_2de1b87f-a750-d1c6-5046-0010aeb97886">The OpenAPI definition SHALL specify for each operation all <link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.0.md#httpCodes">HTTP Status Codes</link> and <link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.0.md#responseObject">Response Objects</link> that the  API uses in responses.</p>
</component><component class="part"><p id="_d029d114-477e-fd62-1f37-014daa3029eb">This includes the successful execution of an operation as well as all error situations that originate from the server.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_668db48d-a20b-d46c-110f-c7bc5fe03645">Note APIs that, for example, are access-controlled (see <xref target="rc_oas30-security">Security</xref>), support web cache validation, support CORS, or that use HTTP redirection will make use of additional HTTP status codes beyond regular codes such as <tt>200</tt> for successful GET requests and <tt>400</tt>, <tt>404</tt> or <tt>500</tt> for error situations. See <xref target="http-status-codes"/>.</p>

<p id="_c4944228-992e-8f95-3b27-6522ed53bda3">Clients should be prepared to receive responses not documented in the OpenAPI definition. For example, additional errors may occur in the transport layer outside of the server.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_oas30-exceptions" obligation="normative">
<title>Exceptions</title>
<requirement id="req_oas30_exceptions-codes"> <label>/req/oas30/exceptions-codes</label><component class="part"><p id="_128019cd-77dc-3bc5-1bf5-a49e3db7c40d">For error situations that originate from an API server, the API definition SHALL cover all applicable HTTP Status Codes.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<example id="_ad830c39-5d3b-356f-3672-fe860375d03c">
<name>An exception response object definition</name>
<sourcecode id="_53ab0e58-9b5d-b9fe-a032-a4b7b3f684f6" lang="YAML">description: An error occurred.
content:
  application/json:
    schema:
      $ref: http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/exception.yaml
  text/html:
    schema:
      type: string</sourcecode>

</example>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_oas30-security" obligation="normative">
<title>Security</title>
<p id="_64ec5375-7e42-9038-ec3d-4940ad47c641">OpenAPI uses two constructs to describe the security features of an API; Security Requirements and Security Schemes. Security Requirements are packaged in an array. Only one of the Security Requirements in the array must be met in-order to authorize a request. Security Requirements are associated with one or more Security Schemes. Each Security Scheme describes a security control (ex. HTTP authentication). All of the security schemes associated with a Security Requirement must be satisfied in order for that Security Requirement to be met.</p>

<p id="_83a58c03-78b7-5620-82b4-cf958abb51fe">Security Requirements can be defined on following levels:</p>

<ul id="_7077fa9b-9d72-2702-8a35-ca4d14b3ef0f"><li><p id="_6a7c58d1-0284-1025-3ba4-5a8b6bd32670">Root — applicable to the whole API except when overridden by Security Requirements defined at a lower level of the API.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_16c8181d-3e05-882d-c0d2-926795de48e1">Operation — only applicable to this operation. Overrides any requirements defined at the Root level.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p id="_44bc9da5-0962-e9bd-284f-0acf2b1a9bde">The OpenAPI specification currently supports the following <link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.3.md#security-scheme-object">security schemes</link>:</p>

<ul id="_2ba121ee-9a0d-a557-8f61-a52b4ed959d5"><li><p id="_55ed4457-d17e-582d-4679-cd24552903d2">HTTP authentication,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_a164689f-c150-dc6c-cf0a-231c35601327">An API key (either as a header or as a query parameter),</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_6b536b7f-fb83-3a5c-2c2c-707e3a932ad5">OAuth2’s common flows (implicit, password, application and access code) as defined in RFC6749, and</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_b6cd21a9-5f70-9140-c7fe-016e841fc29f">OpenID Connect Discovery.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<requirement id="req_oas30_security"> <label>/req/oas30/security</label><component class="part"><p id="_d4d799f0-9c2f-64fd-71cd-e5ae7688ded7">If the operations of the API are access-controlled, the security scheme(s) and requirements SHALL be documented in the OpenAPI definition.</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="rc_oas30-query-parameter" obligation="normative">
<title>Query Parameter Definition</title>
<p id="_d7f22bf6-854f-2b9e-e811-b69ec0270b8a">OpenAPI defines query parameters using the <tt>Parameter</tt> object with the <tt>in</tt> property set to “query”. The parameter name is a literal value provided by the <tt>name</tt> property. Since the parameter names are literals, each parameter must be described separately.</p>

<p id="_e9d3ef81-c34c-bfc7-da11-207e1fac061d">API-Common requires that all query parameters are specified in the API definition. In the case of a Feature server, this could mean that every property of every feature type must be described in the API definition. a requirement that few implementers would accept.</p>

<p id="_4714f91e-5baf-ec8f-fa70-dcf39ba3ca1b">OpenAPI provides a capability that allows additional parameters to be specified without explicitly declaring them. That is, parameters that have not been explicitly specified in the API definition for the operation will still be considered “specified” for purposes of validation (see <xref target="per_core-query-param-name-specified">/per/core/query-param-name-specified</xref> and <xref target="per_core-query-param-name-tolerance">/per/core/query-param-name-tolerance</xref>.</p>

<sourcecode id="schema_free-form" lang="YAML">
<name>OpenAPI schema for additional "free-form" query parameters</name>
in: query
name: freeFormParameters
schema:
  type: object
  additionalProperties: true
style: form</sourcecode>


<p id="_2cc74123-6b6e-553c-e248-95181a3ba891">Note that the name of the parameter does not matter as the actual query parameters are the names of the object properties. For example, assume that the value of <tt>freeFormParameters</tt> is this object:</p>

<sourcecode id="_84892a26-6865-3082-88fd-0bac3b23acc0" lang="JSON">
<name>Example "free-form" query parameter</name>
{
  "my_first_parameter": "some value",
  "my_other_parameter": 42
}</sourcecode>


<p id="_2db4bd65-ece9-e482-a3c3-3f2a1ab56fc6">In the request URI this would be expressed as <tt>&amp;my_first_parameter=some%20value&amp;my_other_parameter=42</tt>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_further_information" obligation="normative">
<title>Further Information</title>
<p id="_21a211e4-a3db-4f33-71f3-2f7b93ae633e">Additional guidance on using OpenAPI in OGC Web API implementations can be found in the <link target="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/DRAFTS/20-071.html#oas30-usage-section">OGC API — Common Users Guide</link>.</p>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="mediatypes-section" obligation="normative">
<title>Media Types</title>
<clause id="mediatypes-response" obligation="normative">
<title>Normal Response Media Types</title>
<p id="_ba429818-ecc1-ad34-cf22-b84a098f2a5f">The typical media type for all “web pages” in an OGC Web API would be <tt>text/html</tt>.</p>

<p id="_fd9791cf-7dd1-6180-9f04-afe4251ec607">The media type that would typically be used in an OGC Web API for machine-to-machine exchanges would be <tt>application/json</tt>.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="mediatypes-oas30" obligation="normative">
<title>OpenAPI Media Types</title>
<p id="_7f33e734-9bec-6636-cfd3-a99610fdc980">The media types for an OpenAPI definition are <tt>application/vnd.oai.openapi+json;version=3.0</tt> (JSON) and <tt>application/vnd.oai.openapi;version=3.0</tt> (YAML).</p>

<note id="_ecf49f81-65c7-7b4f-9dc8-212ccb4966d1"><p id="_5c5bf042-a181-9c2e-a692-5c9c15f9d70c">The OpenAPI media type has not been registered yet with IANA and may change.</p>
</note>
</clause>

<clause id="mediatype-problems" obligation="normative">
<title>Problem Details Media Types</title>
<p id="_fd9e2c49-87bf-4728-f66b-69c33bf2c48f">OGC API-Common recommends that implementers use <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7807" citeas="RFC 7807">IETF RFC 7807</eref> when constructing the response body for an error condition. The media types for an RFC 7807 Problem Details response body are:</p>

<ul id="_9eccc667-e503-daa4-9720-efa6481e9c8b"><li><p id="_f01731ea-c0fa-164c-ad3f-89e910e10dba">application/problem+json — for responses in JSON</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_3d05c4df-0fb4-7077-5bf1-dd50cc2a4001">application/problem+xml — for responses in XML</p>
</li>
</ul>
</clause>
</clause>














</sections><annex id="_abstract_test_suite_normative" obligation="informative">
<title>Abstract Test Suite (Normative)</title>
<clause id="_introduction" obligation="informative">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="_ddab9084-32c4-9b32-b8d7-ad2c92e0659f">OGC Web APIs are not a Web Services in the traditional sense. Rather, they define the behavior and content of a set of Resources exposed through a Web Application Programing Interface (Web API). Therefore, an API may expose resources in addition to those defined by the standard. A test engine must be able to traverse the API, identify and validate test points, and ignore resource paths that are not to be tested.</p>
</clause>

<clause id="_conformance_class_core" obligation="informative">
<title>Conformance Class Core</title>
<requirement id="ats_core" type="conformanceclass"> <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/conf/core"/></label><subject><xref target="rc_core">http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common/1.0/req/core</xref></subject><classification><tag>Target Type</tag><value>Web API</value></classification>
</requirement>

<clause id="_http" obligation="informative">
<title>HTTP</title>
<requirement id="ats_core_http" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/http</label><subject><xref target="req_core_http">/req/core/http</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_da83b8ec-8436-33aa-b695-da4d9f1b285c">Validate that the resources advertised through the API can be accessed using the HTTP 1.1 protocol and, where appropriate, TLS.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><ol id="_94d2eedd-0b7a-9f1a-53c9-04efc2d9e6de" type="arabic"><li><p id="_e2960063-3be6-2915-89ea-111680e36223">All compliance tests shall be configured to use the HTTP 1.1 protocol exclusively.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_aa009e32-a23f-4b85-c2c2-cb56b4194deb">For APIs that support HTTPS, all compliance tests shall be configured to use <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc2818" citeas="RFC 2818">HTTP over TLS</eref> (RFC 2818) with their HTTP 1.1 protocol.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="_query_parameters" obligation="informative">
<title>Query Parameters</title>
<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-name-unknown" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-name-unknown</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-name-unknown">/req/core/query-param-name-unknown</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_22d4cdc7-3c3e-b9a5-fda0-3925b9827e57">Validate that an error is returned when a query parameter is used that has not been specified in the API definition.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_ff43c219-1a7a-0b5f-db8a-b0a14d9c31da">DO FOR ALL operations advertised in the API definition<br/>
  1. Execute that operation using a query parameter that is not specified in the API definition.<br/>
  2. Validate that the operation returns a response with the status code <tt>400</tt>.<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<note id="_3e1fa7d8-b987-d9ea-a349-9cf494a5ec9c"><p id="_6cd97037-f6e8-48cf-3034-0157e2594d77">The parameter name chosen should not fall within the range allowed by  <xref target="per_core-query-param-name-specified">/per/core/query-param-name-specified</xref> or <xref target="per_core-query-param-name-tolerance">/per/core/query-param-name-tolerance</xref>.</p>
</note>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-value-invalid" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-value-invalid</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-value-invalid">/req/core/query-param-value-invalid</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_c24d59d6-b127-af30-ac3c-33cbdbef1d60">Validate that an error is returned when a query parameter contains a value that is not valid for that parameter.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_48880b1a-f37f-3ea5-7241-13d66dd8c177">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Execute that operation using the query parameter with values<br/>
        that do not comply with the advertised constraints on those values.<br/>
        (Example: exceeding minimum or maximum values)<br/>
    2. Validate that the operation returns a response with the status code <tt>400</tt>.<br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<note id="_d1975dfa-ad57-341c-3468-489f96ac31b5"><p id="_03b006a5-4989-2352-42a8-541bcf6d379f">The parameter values chosen should not fall within the range allowed by <xref target="per_core-query-param-value-specified">/per/core/query-param-value-specified</xref> or <xref target="per_core-query-param-value-tolerance">/per/core/query-param-value-tolerance</xref>.</p>
</note>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-capitalization" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-capitalization</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-capitalization">/req/core/query-param-capitalization</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_87b4c8a7-62bd-6216-8227-9f7d13be4245">Validate that a parameter name is correctly capitalized</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_97fc9127-3ebf-3c52-44ae-84765c50a3d3">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Execute that operation using that query parameter<br/>
        capitalized as specified in the API definition<br/>
    2. Validate that the operation returns a response with the status code <tt>200</tt>.<br/>
    3. Execute that operation using that query parameter with captialization<br/>
        inverse of that specified in the API definition<br/>
        (Example: “Range” vs. “rANGE”)<br/>
    4. Validate that the operation returns a response with the status code <tt>400</tt>.<br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-list-delimiter" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-list-delimiter</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-list-delimiter">/req/core/query-param-list-delimiter</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_bcc4938c-3b53-69e9-828d-86207d604c59">For every query parameter where the value may be a list, validate that the server uses the designated delimiter to parse the items from the list.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_d61eff29-296d-40a4-4fba-9cfde693ecdd">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition where the parameter value can be a list<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Generate a request using that parameter and a value that is a delimited <br/>
        list of items. Use a delimiter that is:<br/>
            a. As advertised in the API definition OR<br/>
            b. A comma (“,”) if no delimiter is advertised.<br/>
    2. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value<br/>
    3. Generate a request using that parameter and a value where:<br/>
        a. the value is a delimited list AND<br/>
        b. the delimiter used to construct the list is not valid for this server<br/>
    4. Validate that the server returns a status code <tt>400</tt><br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-list-escape" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-list-escape</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-list-escape">/req/core/query-param-list-escape</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_027b41dc-d17d-7da7-1411-751524e2c9be">For every query parameter where the value may be a list, validate that all escaped space and comma characters that appear in the values are properly processed.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_8d708a67-0a55-a277-c3f2-576628e76aa4">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition where the parameter value can be a list<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Generate a request using that parameter and a value that<br/>
        includes an escaped space or comma<br/>
    2. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value<br/>
    3. Generate a request using that parameter and a value that<br/>
        includes an non-escaped space or comma<br/>
    4. Validate that the server returns a status code <tt>400</tt><br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-list-empty" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-list-empty</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-list-empty">/req/core/query-param-list-empty</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_452eb295-c18f-f540-8bab-bc7a8595ecc6">For every query parameter where the value may be a list, validate that the server interprets an empty string as an empty list.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_43cbf5a7-f69d-5ee8-c040-3a666a19dd29">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition where the parameter value can be a list<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Generate a request using that parameter and an empty string for the parameter value.<br/>
    2. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value as an empty list<br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-value-boolean" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-value-boolean</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-value-boolean">/req/core/query-param-value-boolean</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_e8ed12c4-1c30-230a-5ef4-84c1f82511fc">For every query parameter where the value is a boolean, validate that the server correctly interprets boolean values of “true” and “false”.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_8aa9b3e1-f823-8c2a-7006-4beb62ab7116">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition where the parameter value is a boolean<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Generate a request using that parameter and the string “true” for the parameter value<br/>
    2. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value as true boolean value<br/>
    3. Generate a request using that parameter and the string “false” for the parameter value<br/>
    4. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value as false boolean value<br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-value-integer" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-value-integer</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-value-integer">/req/core/query-param-value-integer</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_8b98f456-46b2-7e58-fb4a-2e9ad4ea4e3a">For every query parameter where the value is an integer, validate that the server correctly interprets properly encoded integer values.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_ecbba882-80b5-2c33-079e-c0218dc2d123">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition where the parameter value is an integer<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Generate a request using that parameter and an unsigned numeric string for the parameter value<br/>
    2. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value as an unsigned integer<br/>
    3. Generate a request using that parameter and a negative signed numeric string for the parameter value<br/>
    4. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value as a signed negative integer value<br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-value-decimal" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-value-decimal</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-value-decimal">/req/core/query-param-value-decimal</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_b4ecbce4-d344-dc6e-15fc-801e2b6ab2b2">For every query parameter where the value is an decimal, validate that the server correctly interprets properly encoded decimal values.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_6cc2e579-825f-c162-fce9-e0f17b7f1fd6">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition where the parameter value is a decimal number<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Generate a request using that parameter and a parameter value that is:<br/>
        a) an unsigned numeric string preceded by one or more zeros<br/>
        b) contains at least two factional digits followed by one or more zeros<br/>
    2. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value as an unsigned decimal value<br/>
    3. Generate a request using that parameter and a parameter value that is:<br/>
        a) a signed negative numeric string<br/>
        b) contains at least two factional digits followed by one or more zeros<br/>
    4. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value as a signed negative decimal value<br/>
    5. Generate a request using that parameter and a parameter value that:<br/>
        a) is an unsigned numeric string preceded by one or more zeros<br/>
        b) does not contain non-numeric characters (“.”)<br/>
    6. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value as an unsigned decimal value with a fractional value of zero<br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_core_query-param-value-double" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/core/query-param-value-double</label><subject><xref target="req_core_query-param-value-double">/req/core/query-param-value-double</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_f69fd4d6-d945-9ce1-5bba-b8eb0812b979">For every query parameter where the value is a double, validate that the server correctly interprets properly encoded double values.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_bc02f184-d6ed-307f-5dbf-d54496d55403">DO FOR ALL query parameters advertised in the API definition where the parameter value is a double value<br/>
  DO FOR ALL operations for which that parameter is valid<br/>
    1. Generate a request using that parameter and a parameter value that is:<br/>
        a) greater than 4,294,967,296 (“e” and exponent required) and<br/>
        b) contains at least two factional digits followed by one or more zeros<br/>
    2. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value<br/>
    3. Generate a request using that parameter and a parameter value that is:<br/>
        a) less than -4,294,967,296 (without “e” and exponent) and<br/>
        b) contains at least two factional digits followed by one or more zeros<br/>
    4. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value<br/>
    5. Generate a request using that parameter and a parameter value that is:<br/>
        a) Less than 4,294,967,296<br/>
        b) Greater than -4,294,967,295<br/>
        c) Represented as a single decimal number<br/>
    6. Validate that the server properly interprets that parameter value<br/>
  DONE<br/>
DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="_conformance_class_landing_page" obligation="informative">
<title>Conformance Class Landing Page</title>
<requirement id="ats_landing-page" type="conformanceclass"> <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/conf/landing-page"/></label><subject><xref target="rc_landing-page">http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common/1.0/req/landing-page</xref></subject><inherit><xref target="ats_core">Core Conformance Class</xref></inherit><classification><tag>Target Type</tag><value>Web API</value></classification>
</requirement>

<clause id="_landing_page" obligation="informative">
<title>Landing Page</title>
<requirement id="ats_landing-page_root-op" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/landing-page/root-op</label><subject><xref target="req_landing-page_root-op">/req/landing-page/root-op</xref><br/>
<xref target="req_landing-page_root-success">/req/landing-page/root-success</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_d6477226-17c4-7643-f36b-aeebae66bee7">Validate that a landing page can be retrieved from the expected location.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><ol id="_35c4f7d8-2f53-7e2a-5cca-2340090f4f52" type="arabic"><li><p id="_00513ad9-3ce5-91c8-67e9-ef0f52776a42">Issue an HTTP GET request to the URL {root}/</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_c0d3a5c5-063a-0aa5-c23e-f7c85c891845">Validate that a document was returned with a status code <tt>200</tt></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_39c65b2a-1e9c-8770-2166-e0d586b42c4c">Validate the contents of the returned document using test <xref target="ats_landing-page_root-success">/conf/landing-page/root-success</xref>.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_landing-page_root-success" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/landing-page/root-success</label><subject><xref target="req_landing-page_root-success">/req/landing-page/root-success</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_8fd01dee-073f-c97b-fb62-8f72fd64d80f">Validate that the landing page complies with the required structure and contents.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_58845f1c-cb1a-6419-8cb2-2678790996c0">Validate the landing page for all supported media types using the resources and tests identified in <xref target="landing-page-schema"/></p>

<p id="_34039eb2-f113-9b22-2ab4-260fbf082090">For formats that require manual inspection, perform the following:</p>

<ol id="_4c99f413-061c-1d56-94e8-819e82ed34c5" type="arabic"><li><p id="_61f98738-d5ab-ba86-4fa2-51780f55cdc4">Validate that the landing page includes a “service-desc” and/or “service-doc” link to an API Definition</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_953e03e6-615f-e9c8-fe01-c4db58162841">Validate that the landing page includes a “http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance” link to the conformance class declaration</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>

<p id="_cfc4aabd-6da3-beb0-516b-96f1385e6680">The landing page may be retrieved in a number of different formats. The following table identifies the applicable schema document for each format and the test to be used to validate the landing page against that schema. All supported formats should be exercised.</p>

<table id="landing-page-schema" width="90%">
<name>Schema and Tests for Landing Pages</name>
<thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left">Format</th>
<th valign="middle" align="left">Schema Document</th>
<th valign="middle" align="left">Test ID</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">HTML</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left"><link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/landingPage.yaml">landingPage.yaml</link></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left"><xref target="ats_html_content">/conf/html/content</xref></td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">JSON</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left"><link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/landingPage.yaml">landingPage.yaml</link></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left"><xref target="ats_json_content">/conf/json/content</xref></td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
</clause>

<clause id="_api_definition" obligation="informative">
<title>API Definition</title>
<requirement id="ats_landing-page_api_definition-op" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/landing-page/api-definition-op</label><subject><xref target="req_landing-page_api-definition-op">/req/landing-page/api-definition-op</xref><br/>
<xref target="req_landing-page_api-definition-success">/req/landing-page/api-definition-success</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_c4fdc479-827a-8178-1514-8e5d8069e364">Validate that the API Definition document can be retrieved from the expected location.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_e5a96576-2203-11bd-f483-cf267e61027d">DO FOR EACH <tt>service-desc</tt> and <tt>service-doc</tt> link on the landing page:</p>

<ol id="_7e1c3f3e-bcdc-5852-d31d-9fe04c28f789" type="arabic"><li><p id="_fd8e1c14-e9c8-d9cc-82fc-4410ef261b07">Issue an HTTP GET request for the link</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_ac7175a6-13b3-20fb-c3e5-61aa53b2a4db">Validate that a document was returned with a status code <tt>200</tt></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_b81f6c99-b173-b968-b6ee-f44c42d25bf3">Validate the contents of the returned document using test <xref target="ats_landing-page_api-definition-success">/conf/landing-page/api-definition-success</xref>.</p>
</li>
</ol>

<p id="_d9a08072-04e7-f521-7889-a22bf8ebe827">DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_landing-page_api-definition-success" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/landing-page/api-definition-success</label><subject><xref target="req_landing-page_api-definition-success">/req/landing-page/api-definition-success</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_8bb27e1f-6475-8d33-1971-4b5971a2b870">Validate that the API Definition complies with the required structure and contents.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_9b2cefd4-5e80-7ad7-7eee-ca1f473f09cd">Validate the API Definition document against an appropriate schema document.</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="_conformance_declaration" obligation="informative">
<title>Conformance Declaration</title>
<requirement id="ats_landing-page_conformance-op" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/landing-page/conformance-op</label><subject><xref target="req_landing-page_conformance-op">/req/landing-page/conformance-op</xref><br/>
<xref target="req_landing-page_conformance-success">/req/landing-page/conformance-success</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_a63c063a-64f9-1af4-4283-f99ea3610c62">Validate that a Conformance Declaration can be retrieved from the expected locations.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_abbebcf4-30f6-75fa-6d19-f832e7328ec6">DO FOR EACH <tt><link target="http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance"/></tt> link on the landing page:</p>

<ol id="_eaff7cd3-9c19-1a0c-551d-7c8a6b0a378a" type="arabic"><li><p id="_95e7aa6f-c424-2694-b5d8-1965d3c46563">Issue an HTTP GET request for the link</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_0a9810e2-d653-e014-a6c3-a932bf2cd8cb">Validate that a document was returned with a status code <tt>200</tt></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_b1a8b558-832f-2a8a-7fa9-df393ad3787e">Validate the contents of the returned document using test <xref target="ats_landing-page_conformance-success">/conf/landing-page/conformance-success</xref>.</p>
</li>
</ol>

<p id="_bb584f19-aaba-d229-605c-5a31760050fa">DONE</p>

<ol id="_46202475-344a-3e85-8b81-7d55dafd5b2f" type="arabic"><li><p id="_f8652f36-8e15-47e9-22f3-24ac067a936d">Issue an HTTP GET request for the <tt>{root}/conformance</tt> path</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_8df3e201-eeba-ceb9-b04d-b5c5c94610ef">Validate that a document was returned with a status code <tt>200</tt></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_3fd23001-4b3e-49b7-0c4a-36f1e93b0b09">Validate the contents of the returned document using test <xref target="ats_landing-page_conformance-success">/conf/landing-page/conformance-success</xref>.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_landing-page_conformance-success" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/landing-page/conformance-success</label><subject><xref target="req_landing-page_conformance-success">/req/landing-page/conformance-success</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_8b030508-67f6-4abe-4b43-c5bd23dd2ece">Validate that the Conformance Declaration response complies with the required structure and contents.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><ol id="_b28316e9-0cdd-1504-220b-0777bebd8410" type="arabic"><li><p id="_1264cfd2-8542-ae45-fc07-d0d60a0a3a70">Validate the response document against the schema <link target="http://schemas.opengis.net/ogcapi/common/part1/1.0/openapi/schemas/confClasses.yaml">confClasses.yaml</link></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_aca23b5a-6f0d-d8fe-3be3-63d2d923b2ce">Validate that the document list all OGC API conformance classes that the API implements.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="_conformance_class_json" obligation="informative">
<title>Conformance Class JSON</title>
<requirement id="ats_json" type="conformanceclass"> <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/conf/json"/></label><subject><xref target="rc_json">http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/json</xref></subject><inherit><xref target="ats_core">Core Conformance Class</xref></inherit><inherit><xref target="ats_landing-page">Landing Page Conformance Class</xref></inherit><classification><tag>Target Type</tag><value>Web API</value></classification>
</requirement>

<clause id="_json_definition" obligation="informative">
<title>JSON Definition</title>
<requirement id="ats_json_definition" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/json/definition</label><subject><xref target="req_json_definition">/req/json/definition</xref><br/>
<xref target="req_json_content">/req/json/content</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_b18da86f-ae9c-208a-250e-4cc17fdf0cf0">Verify support for JSON</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_a03a39bf-abab-15ba-a55f-b7f247360185">DO FOR EACH resource and operation defined in the Landing Page Conformance Class:</p>

<ol id="_70841397-ff7d-96fd-22eb-3d2f94d893e2" type="arabic"><li><p id="_cbe670e9-5baf-4803-4d67-2f591f2c59b7">Execute the operation specifying <tt>application/json</tt> as the media type</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_d48bd55f-1e15-3d3a-4b0f-2b8521f506c1">Validate that a document was returned with a status code <tt>200</tt></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_4475556a-0376-cd64-e4ab-86332a8efa47">Validate the contents of the returned document using test <xref target="ats_json_content">/conf/json/content</xref>.</p>
</li>
</ol>

<p id="_2f7e2219-5781-087f-5547-26f573f227e1">DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="_json_content" obligation="informative">
<title>JSON Content</title>
<requirement id="ats_json_content" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/json/content</label><subject><xref target="req_json_content">/req/json/content</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_439de9db-ce7e-fa44-1146-80da0b0067bd">Verify the content of a JSON document given an input document and schema.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><ol id="_25f802d4-d86f-fd19-dcbe-c19256a58b46" type="arabic"><li><p id="_49e3550c-e7dc-82ba-3092-2b4d2daac343">Validate that the document is a <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc8259" citeas="RFC 8259">JSON (IETF RFC 8259)</eref> document.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_082541ec-46e8-9883-d81d-8fef24f2307e">Validate the document against the schema using a JSON Schema validator.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="_conformance_class_html" obligation="informative">
<title>Conformance Class HTML</title>
<requirement id="ats_html" type="conformanceclass"> <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/conf/html"/></label><subject><xref target="rc_html">http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common/1.0/req/html</xref></subject><inherit><xref target="ats_core">Core Conformance Class</xref></inherit><inherit><xref target="ats_landing-page">Landing Page Conformance Class</xref></inherit><classification><tag>Target Type</tag><value>Web API</value></classification>
</requirement>

<clause id="_html_definition" obligation="informative">
<title>HTML Definition</title>
<requirement id="ats_html_definition" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/html/definition</label><subject><xref target="req_html_definition">/req/html/definition</xref><br/>
<xref target="req_html_content">/req/html/content</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_e95aa682-446c-c749-2437-7acf46fb8ce3">Verify support for HTML</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_d5e381b8-e357-0cea-ef86-ed1169be85d4">DO FOR EACH resource and operation defined in the Landing Page Conformance Class:</p>

<ol id="_ae35678a-344b-8c7e-5e49-0e748319988a" type="arabic"><li><p id="_53004a33-4e67-676c-978c-8d5dba9cf549">Execute the operation specifying <tt>text/html</tt> as the media type</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_89b02751-529d-15f8-0411-2a1d6f377a1a">Validate that a document was returned with a status code <tt>200</tt></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_e8ec564e-46de-d1c2-b433-cad785cb1a35">Validate the contents of the returned document using test <xref target="ats_html_content">/conf/html/content</xref>.</p>
</li>
</ol>

<p id="_0b75b11b-3419-5376-3e7e-a252a90f16f8">DONE</p>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>

<clause id="_html_content" obligation="informative">
<title>HTML Content</title>
<requirement id="ats_html_content" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/html/content</label><subject><xref target="req_html_content">/req/html/content</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_f0ce0847-c180-7327-ed55-1a21777bc986">Verify the content of an HTML document given an input document and schema.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><ol id="_045f0141-c31a-1abb-a993-9d924fe9e4f6" type="arabic"><li><p id="_b309055b-2754-0b89-a290-5db3e42bb047">Validate that the document is an <link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/html5/">HTML 5 document</link></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_b98d00d5-dde1-9283-65dd-c8a8f9c89e64">Manually inspect the document against the schema.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>
</clause>

<clause id="_conformance_class_openapi_3_0" obligation="informative">
<title>Conformance Class OpenAPI 3.0</title>
<requirement id="_138d4e18-c779-c3ec-859d-3aa966f164f3" type="conformanceclass"> <label><link target="http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/conf/oas30"/></label><subject><xref target="rc_oas30">http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common/1.0/req/oas30</xref></subject><inherit><xref target="ats_core">Core Conformance Class</xref></inherit><inherit><xref target="ats_landing-page">Landing Page Conformance Class</xref></inherit><classification><tag>Target Type</tag><value>Web API</value></classification>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_oas30_completeness" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/oas30/completeness</label><subject><xref target="req_oas30_completeness">/req/oas30/completeness</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_93f213d8-7c7e-d0ed-8762-591d27a5953c">Verify the completeness of an OpenAPI document.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_5d30e85b-ee74-d206-757a-8ca1a9e2a94a">Verify that for each operation, the OpenAPI document describes all <link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.0.md#httpCodes">HTTP Status Codes</link> and <link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.0.md#responseObject">Response Objects</link> that the API uses in responses.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_oas30_exceptions-codes" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/oas30/exceptions-codes</label><subject><xref target="req_oas30_exceptions-codes">/req/oas30/exceptions-codes</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_b319fb4d-98de-9348-6b82-a144a30a8814">Verify that the OpenAPI document fully describes potential exception codes.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_70cf3603-2f30-d4af-22c6-3fc78db0b4cc">Verify that for each operation, the OpenAPI document describes all <link target="https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification/blob/master/versions/3.0.0.md#httpCodes">HTTP Status Codes</link> that may be generated.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_oas30_oas-definition-1" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/oas30/oas-definition-1</label><subject><xref target="req_oas30_oas-definition-1">/req/oas30/oas-definition-1</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_efc17e04-0286-ca8e-e211-b6edb3fcfb6b">Verify that JSON and HTML versions of the OpenAPI document are available.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><ol id="_dc4311f8-7f3c-f9c8-da68-e1b82e9afd09" type="arabic"><li><p id="_c3e6b8fb-228f-54e5-d9ce-c3e0a169001c">Verify that an OpenAPI definition in JSON is available using the media type <tt>application/vnd.oai.openapi+json;version=3.0</tt> and link relation <tt>service-desc</tt></p>
</li>
<li><p id="_b587a96c-0d9e-bda9-a2b5-402513a75a6f">Verify that an HTML version of the API definition is available using the media type <tt>text/html</tt> and link relation <tt>service-doc</tt>.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_oas30_oas-definition-2" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/oas30/oas-definition-2</label><subject><xref target="req_oas30_oas-definition-2">/req/oas30/oas-definition-2</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_72bc67b2-e890-a8a4-cc7a-71b9c2fae9b5">Verify that the OpenAPI document is valid JSON.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><p id="_491adc5c-a36b-ea33-3dfc-ffebbac657c6">Verify that the JSON representation conforms to the <eref type="inline" bibitemid="openapi" citeas="openapi">OpenAPI Specification, version 3.0</eref>.</p>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_oas30_oas-impl" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/oas30/oas-impl</label><subject><xref target="req_oas30_oas-impl">/req/oas30/oas-impl</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_59f530f3-07b8-7389-93c2-77000655a235">Verify that all capabilities specified in the OpenAPI definition are implemented by the API.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><ol id="_b202bf59-73f0-81e0-efcd-91ca19b9bfe4" type="arabic"><li><p id="_8edd2f01-9d6c-01ba-11a1-8c833543eabc">Construct an operation for each OpenAPI <tt>Path</tt> object including all server URL options, HTTP operations and enumerated path parameters.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_49abe594-ef96-03df-305c-bc086207c8d3">Validate that each operation performs in accordance with the API definition.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>

<requirement id="ats_oas30_security" type="abstracttest"> <label>/conf/oas30/security</label><subject><xref target="req_oas30_security">/req/oas30/security</xref></subject><component class="test-purpose"><p id="_624f7f12-384a-5aec-0a8e-ce51f5dcd5cf">Verify that any authentication protocols implemented by the API are documented in the OpenAPI document.</p>
</component><component class="test-method"><ol id="_55fe280a-9188-2dc4-037f-9bd6cf1e39c7" type="arabic"><li><p id="_f6c2355f-7854-a32d-166a-2590c4f2ed2c">Identify all authentication protocols supported by the API.</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_bcba13d6-b4ab-9728-9212-99842af10a76">Validate that each authentication protocol is described in the OpenAPI document by a Security Schema Object and its use specified by a Security Requirement Object.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</component>
</requirement>
</clause>
</annex><annex id="_examples_informative" obligation="informative">
<title>Examples (Informative)</title>
<clause id="landing-page-examples" obligation="informative">
<title>Example Landing Pages</title>
<example id="json-landing-page">
<name>JSON Landing Page</name>
<p id="_309284da-508b-8560-40e9-203104124aaf">This example Landing Page response in JSON is for an implementation of the OGC API-Common Standard that supports:</p>

<ul id="_d1c422ee-98c9-edc6-cb30-be15699be553"><li><p id="_3a64fda2-d7a9-cad3-c880-2f22d53cc4b7">HTML</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_5216995a-b3ac-912b-52d9-a88b7455ebac">JSON</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_9bce378a-304e-d407-ab13-5ff52347516f">API-Common Part 2 (Geospatial Data)</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p id="_3538b5df-167b-dfc1-8f72-2d07a23b2dc1">This example also illustrates the <tt>self</tt> and <tt>alternate</tt> association types.</p>

<sourcecode id="_aff50a40-e65b-a509-c102-73d3ca5b91ed" lang="json">{
    "title": "Example API Landing Page",
    "description": "This is an example of an API landing page in JSON format",
    "attribution": "&lt;a href='www.ign.es' rel=' '&gt;IGN&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='www.govdata.de/dl-de/by-2-0'&gt;(c)&lt;/a&gt;",
    "links": [
        {
            "rel": "service-desc",
            "type": "application/json",
            "title": "API definition for this endpoint as JSON",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/api?f=application/json"
        },
        {
            "rel": "service-desc",
            "type": "text/html",
            "title": "API definition for this endpoint as HTML",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/api?f=text/html"
        },
        {
            "rel": "http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data-meta",
            "type": "application/xml",
            "title": "ISO 19115 Metadata as XML",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/data-meta?f=application/xml"
        },
        {
            "rel": "http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance",
            "type": "application/json",
            "title": "Conformance Declaration as JSON",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/conformance?f=application/json"
        },
        {
            "rel": "http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance",
            "type": "application/xml",
            "title": "Conformance Declaration as XML",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/conformance?f=application/xml"
        },
        {
            "rel": "http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance",
            "type": "text/html",
            "title": "Conformance Declaration as HTML",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/conformance?f=text/html"
        },
        {
            "rel": "http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data",
            "type": "application/json",
            "title": "Collections Metadata as JSON",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/collections?f=application/json"
        },
        {
            "rel": "http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data",
            "type": "application/xml",
            "title": "Collections Metadata as XML",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/collections?f=application/xml"
        },
        {
            "rel": "http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data",
            "type": "text/html",
            "title": "Collections Metadata as HTML",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c/collections?f=text/html"
        },
        {
            "rel": "self",
            "type": "application/json",
            "title": "This Document",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c?f=application/json"
        },
        {
            "rel": "alternate",
            "type": "application/xml",
            "title": "This Document as XML",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c?f=application/xml"
        },
        {
            "rel": "alternate",
            "type": "text/html",
            "title": "This Document as HTML",
            "href": "http://www.example.com/oapi-c?f=text/html"
        }
    ]
}</sourcecode>


<p id="_607ddd04-6054-7de7-e5bc-cd1d20bbe6b6">The example is presented below in YAML.</p>

<sourcecode id="_d69a635c-012e-2034-13a4-28f02a10af08" lang="YAML">title: Example API Landing Page
description: This is an example of an API landing page in JSON format
attribution: "&lt;a href='www.ign.es' rel=' '&gt;IGN&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='www.govdata.de/dl-de/by-2-0'&gt;(c)&lt;/a&gt;"
links:
- rel: service-desc
  type: application/json
  title: API definition for this endpoint as JSON
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/api?f=application/json
- rel: service-desc
  type: text/html
  title: API definition for this endpoint as HTML
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/api?f=text/html
- rel: http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data-meta
  type: application/xml
  title: ISO 19115 Metadata as XML
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/data-meta?f=application/xml
- rel: http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance
  type: application/json
  title: Conformance Declaration as JSON
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/conformance?f=application/json
- rel: http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance
  type: application/xml
  title: Conformance Declaration as XML
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/conformance?f=application/xml
- rel: http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/conformance
  type: text/html
  title: Conformance Declaration as HTML
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/conformance?f=text/html
- rel: http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data
  type: application/json
  title: Collections Metadata as JSON
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/collections?f=application/json
- rel: http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data
  type: application/xml
  title: Collections Metadata as XML
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/collections?f=application/xml
- rel: http://www.opengis.net/def/rel/ogc/1.0/data
  type: text/html
  title: Collections Metadata as HTML
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c/collections?f=text/html
- rel: self
  type: application/json
  title: This Document
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c?f=application/json
- rel: alternate
  type: application/xml
  title: This Document as XML
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c?f=application/xml
- rel: alternate
  type: text/html
  title: This Document as HTML
  href: http://www.example.com/oapi-c?f=text/html</sourcecode>

</example>
</clause>

<clause id="conformance-response-examples" obligation="informative">
<title>Conformance Examples</title>
<example id="_41b9e984-2c29-f3ee-1a42-173df051b6c1">
<name>Conformance Response</name>
<p id="_00a74c0b-63a0-7446-4c1a-61060c100b5a">This example response in JSON is for an implementation of the OGC API-Common Standard that supports OpenAPI 3.0 for the API definition and HTML and JSON as encodings for resources.</p>

<sourcecode id="_a3a9af5e-3ade-520d-cfce-6a6b8c86fb78" lang="json">{
  "conformsTo": [
    "http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/core",
    "http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/landing-page",
    "http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/oas30",
    "http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/html",
    "http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/json"
  ]
}</sourcecode>


<p id="_bfd89e34-0d5f-4d1d-dcda-a0e339de85d9">The example is presented below in YAML.</p>

<sourcecode id="_71f3808a-2faf-c398-bf47-00138f9449cc" lang="YAML">conformsTo:
- http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/core
- http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/landing-page
- http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/oas30
- http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/html
- http://www.opengis.net/spec/ogcapi-common-1/1.0/req/json</sourcecode>

</example>
</clause>

<clause id="oas-examples" obligation="informative">
<title>API Definition Examples</title>
<example id="json-api-definition">
<name>JSON API Definition</name>
<p id="_4ba65305-1684-0326-8c34-7407caf15b7d">This is an example of an API Definition response in JSON (YAML). It describes an implementation of the OGC API-Common Part 1 — Core Standard.</p>

<p id="_0a7f286d-8af3-3434-4dc9-237a54fde46a">This example also illustrates:</p>

<ol id="_ad5c585f-0fbc-12f4-f332-7f447765b6c0" type="arabic"><li><p id="_d7eed6b8-d08d-4114-69b2-69ec687268a1">Extended metadata (x-keywords),</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_1317c004-68c4-e337-7589-0cb203e14574">Multiple Servers,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_6673aff0-62bb-bb8d-0982-16888a34daab">The use of tags to associate external documentation,</p>
</li>
<li><p id="_216c0e85-5f0a-5b74-5aa1-d60be835b268">Responses that reference the appropriate JSON schema</p>
</li>
</ol>

<sourcecode id="_6bdfe39d-ce98-455d-1f09-aefc039e23e8" lang="YAML">openapi: 3.0.2
info:
  title: &gt;-
    A sample API conforming to the draft standard OGC API - Common - Part 1:
    Core
  version: 1.0.0
  description: &gt;-
    'This is a sample OpenAPI definition of the draft standard OGC API - Common - Part 1: Core.'
  contact:
    name: Acme Corporation
    email: info@example.org
    url: http://example.org/
  license:
    name: CC-BY 4.0 license
    url: https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
  x-keywords:
    - geospatial
    - data
    - api
servers:
  - url: https://data.example.org/
    description: Production server
  - url: https://dev.example.org/
    description: Development server
tags:
  - name: Capabilities
    description: essential characteristics of this API
  - name: server
    description: Information about the server hosting this API
    externalDocs:
      description: information
      url: https://example.com/sample_api/documentation
paths:
  /:
    get:
      description: &gt;-
        The landing page provides links to the API definition and the
        conformance statements for this API.
      parameters:
        - $ref: '#/components/parameters/f'
      operationId: getLandingPage
      responses:
        '200':
          $ref: 'https://raw.githubusercontent.com/opengeospatial/ogcapi-common/master/core/openapi/3.0/API-Common-Part-1_1_0.yaml#/components/responses/LandingPage'
        '400':
          $ref: '#/components/responses/400'
        '500':
          $ref: '#/components/responses/500'
      summary: Landing page
      tags:
        - server
  /api:
    get:
      description: This document
      parameters:
        - $ref: '#/components/parameters/f'
      responses:
        '200':
          $ref: '#/components/responses/200'
        '400':
          $ref: '#/components/responses/400'
        default:
          $ref: '#/components/responses/400'
      summary: This document
      tags:
        - server
  /conformance:
    get:
      description: &gt;-
        A list of all conformance classes specified in a standard that the
        server conforms to.
      parameters:
        - $ref: '#/components/parameters/f'
      operationId: getConformanceDeclaration
      responses:
        '200':
          $ref: 'https://raw.githubusercontent.com/opengeospatial/ogcapi-common/master/core/openapi/3.0/API-Common-Part-1_1_0.yaml#/components/responses/ConfClasses'
        '400':
          $ref: '#/components/responses/400'
        '500':
          $ref: '#/components/responses/500'
      summary: API conformance definition
      tags:
        - server
components:
  parameters:
    f:
      description: &gt;-
        The optional f parameter indicates the output format that the server
        shall provide as part of the response document.  The default format is JSON.
      explode: false
      in: query
      name: f
      required: false
      schema:
        default: json
        enum:
          - json
          - html
        type: string
      style: form
  responses:
    '200':
      description: successful operation
    '400':
      $ref: 'https://raw.githubusercontent.com/opengeospatial/ogcapi-common/master/core/openapi/3.0/API-Common-Part-1_1_0.yaml#/components/responses/400'
    '500':
      $ref: 'https://raw.githubusercontent.com/opengeospatial/ogcapi-common/master/core/openapi/3.0/API-Common-Part-1_1_0.yaml#/components/responses/500'</sourcecode>

</example>
</clause>

<clause id="service-metadata-examples" obligation="informative">
<title>Service Metadata Examples</title>
<example id="service-metadata">
<name>Service Metadata</name>
<p id="_bbe04887-e45d-ea59-564f-2f3be574dd2e">This is an example of how to extend the OpenAPI <tt>info</tt> object to include identifying metadata about both the service and the service provider.</p>

<sourcecode id="_f491b2d7-0119-5717-9c02-764a2b9e274e" lang="YAML">info:
  title: My Web API
  version: 1.0.0
  description: This example shows population of an OpenAPI Info element with identifying
    metadata for both the service and the service provider.
  contact:
    name: Acme Corporation
    email: info@example.org
    url: http://example.org/
    x-OGC-serviceContact:
      individualName: John Smith
      positionName: System Administrator
      role: pointOfcontact
      hoursOfService: 24 Hours
      contractInstructions: None
      onlineResource: http://example.org/contact
      address:
        deliveryPoint: 123 Any Street
        city: Boston
        administrativeArea: MA
        postalCode: '12345'
        country: USA
        electronicMailAddress: smith.j@example.org
      telephone:
        voice: "+1.123.456.7890"
        facsimile: "+1.123.456.7890 "
  license:
    name: CC-BY 4.0 license
    url: https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
  x-serviceType: http://www.opengis.net/doc/IS/ogcapi-common-1/1.0
  x-serviceTypeVersion: '1.0'
  x-profile: DGIWG
  x-keywords:
  - geospatial
  - data
  - api
  x-fees: None
  x-accessConstraints: None</sourcecode>

</example>
</clause>
</annex><annex id="_3036ad6f-2b3c-c274-f1fd-2836cfb56d5f" obligation="informative">
<title>Glossary</title>
<terms id="Glossary" obligation="normative"><ul id="ctm-definition"><li><p id="_6b88b727-a94c-784d-4bb7-977f1a4bb429"><strong>Conformance Test Module</strong><br/>
set of related tests, all within a single conformance test class (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="ogc08-131" citeas="[11]">OGC 08-131</eref>)</p>
</li>
</ul>

<note id="_1589a364-cbcd-8b8c-b15a-2e00d3254c4a"><p id="_1cf7d68b-df21-208b-d01f-8d5473a1cda2">When no ambiguity is possible, the word <tt>test</tt> may be omitted. i.e. <xref target="ctm-definition">conformance test module</xref> is the same as <xref target="ctm-definition">conformance module</xref>. Conformance modules may be nested in a hierarchical way. This term and those associated to it are included here for consistency with ISO 19105.</p>
</note>

<ul id="ctc-definition"><li><p id="_33a7f74d-cae8-5cd8-aae0-4372672ed0b2"><strong>Conformance Test Class; Conformance Test Level</strong><br/>
set of <xref target="ctm-definition">conformance test modules</xref> that must be applied to receive a single <strong>certificate of conformance</strong>. (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="ogc08-131" citeas="[11]">OGC 08-131</eref>)</p>
</li>
</ul>

<note id="_e88bf2d1-66ae-d61f-1868-43b10e1f4e4c"><p id="_f2b7cf80-b5a4-14c6-561c-46be3bb272b9">When no ambiguity is possible, the word <tt>test</tt> may be left out, so <xref target="ctc-definition">conformance test class</xref> may be called a <xref target="ctc-definition">conformance class</xref>.</p>
</note>

<ul id="ets-definition"><li><p id="_d324993d-2fcd-008a-74e3-ce8875438c57"><strong>Executable Test Suite (ETS)</strong><br/>
A set of code (e.g. Java and CTL) that provides runtime tests for the assertions defined by the ATS. Test data required to do the tests are part of the ETS <link target="https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=55234">(OGC 08-134)</link></p>
</li>
</ul>

<ul id="recomendation-definition"><li><p id="_98b194ba-8b10-4403-9bb3-de61c74844a0"><strong>Recommendation</strong><br/>
expression in the content of a document conveying that among several possibilities one is recommended as particularly suitable, without mentioning or excluding others, or that a certain course of action is preferred but not necessarily required, or that (in the negative form) a certain possibility or course of action is deprecated but not prohibited (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="ogc08-131" citeas="[11]">OGC 08-131</eref>)</p>
</li>
</ul>

<note id="_3adf2d09-99ef-aec1-9455-9bd339a35a9b"><p id="_8e9dea7d-54e6-07bd-612b-2a86acf882c8">“Although using normative language, a <xref target="recomendation-definition">recommendation</xref> is not a <xref target="requirement-definition">requirement</xref>. The usual form replaces the <tt>shall</tt> (imperative or command) of a <xref target="requirement-definition">requirement</xref> with a <tt>should</tt> (suggestive or conditional).” (ISO Directives Part 2)</p>
</note>

<ul id="requirement-definition"><li><p id="_8f51bf7e-1c5b-c20d-7cc9-d0512099abdc"><strong>Requirement</strong><br/>
expression in the content of a document conveying criteria to be fulfilled if compliance with the document is to be claimed and from which no deviation is permitted (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="ogc08-131" citeas="[11]">OGC 08-131</eref>)</p>
</li>
</ul>

<ul id="requirements-class-definition"><li><p id="_5f78b4c9-2317-6ea9-e649-590b1470baf3"><strong>Requirements Class</strong><br/>
aggregate of all requirement modules that must all be satisfied to satisfy a conformance test class (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="ogc08-131" citeas="[11]">OGC 08-131</eref>)</p>
</li>
</ul>

<ul id="requirements-module-definition"><li><p id="_0f0d675d-d268-21d6-4b92-7609c0bf6968"><strong>Requirements Module</strong><br/>
aggregate of <xref target="requirement-definition">requirements</xref> and <xref target="recomendation-definition">recommendations</xref> of a specification against a single <xref target="standardization-target-definition">standardization target</xref> type (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="ogc08-131" citeas="[11]">OGC 08-131</eref>)</p>
</li>
</ul>

<ul id="standardization-target-definition"><li><p id="_6a2a9d17-ed2f-4bb8-4185-129159f15163"><strong>Standardization Target</strong><br/>
entity to which some requirements of a standard apply (<eref type="inline" bibitemid="ogc08-131" citeas="[11]">OGC 08-131</eref>)</p>
</li>
</ul>

<note id="_73471089-7f73-cbe9-0eb1-625bcdf9d156"><p id="_dcc85693-7acf-fcb3-cee0-86e2baad2c35">The standardization target is the entity that may receive a certificate of conformance for a requirements class.</p>
</note>
</terms>
</annex><annex id="bnf-annex" obligation="informative">
<title>Backus-Naur Forms</title>
<clause id="uri-bnf-annex" obligation="informative">
<title>BNF for URI</title>
<p id="_0fc609d2-e82d-aae9-53e5-98bbc46da6f6">The following Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) is from Appendix A of <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc3986" citeas="RFC 3986">IETF RFC 3986</eref>.</p>

<sourcecode id="_1cc1ae7b-ea01-5935-ae14-c629bce6eca2">
<name>Backus-Naur Form for URI</name>
  URI           = scheme ":" hier-part [ "?" query ] [ "#" fragment ]

  hier-part     = "//" authority path-abempty
               / path-absolute
               / path-rootless
               / path-empty

  URI-reference = URI / relative-ref

  absolute-URI  = scheme ":" hier-part [ "?" query ]

  relative-ref  = relative-part [ "?" query ] [ "#" fragment ]

  relative-part = "//" authority path-abempty
                   / path-absolute
                   / path-noscheme
                   / path-empty

  scheme        = ALPHA *( ALPHA / DIGIT / "+" / "-" / "." )

  authority     = [ userinfo "@" ] host [ ":" port ]
  userinfo      = *( unreserved / pct-encoded / sub-delims / ":" )
  host          = IP-literal / IPv4address / reg-name
  port          = *DIGIT

  IP-literal    = "[" ( IPv6address / IPvFuture  ) "]"

  IPvFuture     = "v" 1*HEXDIG "." 1*( unreserved / sub-delims / ":" )

  IPv6address   =                             6( h16 ":" ) ls32
                /                       "::" 5( h16 ":" ) ls32
                / [               h16 ] "::" 4( h16 ":" ) ls32
                / [ *1( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::" 3( h16 ":" ) ls32
                / [ *2( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::" 2( h16 ":" ) ls32
                / [ *3( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::"    h16 ":"   ls32
                / [ *4( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::"              ls32
                / [ *5( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::"              h16
                / [ *6( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::"

  h16           = 1*4HEXDIG
  ls32          = ( h16 ":" h16 ) / IPv4address
  IPv4address   = dec-octet "." dec-octet "." dec-octet "."

  dec-octet     = DIGIT                 ; 0-9
                / %x31-39 DIGIT         ; 10-99
                / "1" 2DIGIT            ; 100-199
                / "2" %x30-34 DIGIT     ; 200-249
                / "25" %x30-35          ; 250-255

  reg-name      = *( unreserved / pct-encoded / sub-delims )

  path          = path-abempty    ; begins with "/" or is empty
                / path-absolute   ; begins with "/" but not "//"
                / path-noscheme   ; begins with a non-colon segment
                / path-rootless   ; begins with a segment
                / path-empty      ; zero characters

  path-abempty  = *( "/" segment )
  path-absolute = "/" [ segment-nz *( "/" segment ) ]
  path-noscheme = segment-nz-nc *( "/" segment )
  path-rootless = segment-nz *( "/" segment )
  path-empty    = 0&lt;pchar&gt;

  segment       = *pchar
  segment-nz    = 1*pchar
  segment-nz-nc = 1*( unreserved / pct-encoded / sub-delims / "@" )
                ; non-zero-length segment without any colon ":"

  pchar         = unreserved / pct-encoded / sub-delims / ":" / "@"

  query         = *( pchar / "/" / "?" )

  fragment      = *( pchar / "/" / "?" )

  pct-encoded   = "%" HEXDIG HEXDIG

  unreserved    = ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "." / "_" / "~"
  reserved      = gen-delims / sub-delims
  gen-delims    = ":" / "/" / "?" / "#" / "[" / "]" / "@"
  sub-delims    = "!" / "$" / "&amp;" / "'" / "(" / ")"
                / "*" / "+" / "," / ";" / "="</sourcecode>

</clause>
</annex><annex id="_ogc_web_api_guidelines" obligation="informative">
<title>OGC Web API Guidelines</title>
<p id="_1b48cff8-89e0-baee-b87b-61bcee7fb9c4">The following table discusses how this standard addresses the design principles documented in the <link target="https://github.com/opengeospatial/OGC-Web-API-Guidelines">OGC Web API Guidelines</link>.</p>

<table id="web-api-guidelines"><colgroup><col width="9.0909%"/><col width="18.1818%"/><col width="72.7273%"/></colgroup>
<name>OGC Web API Guidelines</name>
<thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center"><strong>#</strong></th>
<th valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Principle</strong></th>
<th valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Discussion</strong></th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">1</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Don’t reinvent</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Great care was taken in the development of this standard to only address capabilities that were not already standardized and to define how the needed capabilites integrate into a single API.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">2</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Keep it simple and intuitive</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">OGC Web APIs are developed using a building block approach. Conformance Classes are defined that encompase requirements sufficient to create a usable software module and no more. Complex APIs are constructed by assembling the applicable Conformance Classes.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">3</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Use well-known resource types</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Except where unique to a specific Conformance Class, all resources types are IANA or OGC registered types.<br/>
OGC Web API standards do not mandate an encoding. The encodings supported by an API are specified by the corresponding encoding Conformance Classes. All encodings used to-date are IANA registered media types.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">4</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Construct consistent URIs</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">OGC Web APIs are built from standardized modules using standardized patterns. This modular approach assures that the URIs are consistent across OGC Web APIs.<br/>
OGC Web API Common defines stylistic conventions for query parameters, query values, identifiers, and path elements used to create OGC Web API URIs.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">5</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Use HTTP methods consistent with RFC 7231</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">OGC web APIs are restricted to the HTTP methods defined in IETF <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">RFC 7231</eref>.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">6</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Put selection criteria behind the ‘?’</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left"><xref target="identifier-conventions">Section 6.1</xref> of this Standard defines the conventions to be used when creating URIs for OGC Web API standards. This includes the use of the “?” to deliminate query parameters from the rest of the URI.<br/>
Note that this does not preclude the use of resource identifiers (ex. collection identifiers) as part of the path. However those can be considered identifying criteria rather than selection criteria.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">7</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Error handling and use of HTTP status codes</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">This standard identifies the applicable HTTP status codes and under what conditions they should be returned. Status codes and supporting information are returned in the HTTP response using a reporting structure based on RFC 7807.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">8</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Use explicit list of HTTP status codes</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left"><xref target="http-status-codes"/> provides a list of the HTTP status codes that implementers of this standard should be prepared to generate and accept. This list is not exhaustive (see guideline #1).</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">9</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Use of HTTP header</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">OGC API Common does not preclude use of HTTP headers where it is appropriate to do so.<br/>
Only standard HTTP headers are used.<br/>
Due to the common use of the HATEOAS pattern in OGC Web APIs, HTTP headers are not always accessible. The use of query parameter overrides is allowed.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">10</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Allow flexible content negotiation</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">IETF <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">RFC 7231</eref> content negotiation is avalable on all transactions.<br/>
Since the HTTP headers are not always accessible, content negotiation may be performed through a query parameter (see #9).</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">11</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Pagination</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Of the resources defined in API-Common Core only the conformance resource is “listable”. We do not anticipate the conformance resource to grow to any size, so support for pagenation would add complexity will little to no value (violating #2)<br/>
If an OpenAPI document is used as the API definition, then pagination could become an issue for this resource. The question of how to handle large OpenAPI documents is still an open issue being worked across the Standards Working Groups.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">12</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Processing resources</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Processing resources are not addressed by this Standard.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">13</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Support metadata</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Support for metadata is provided through metadata resource links. Examples include links with the relation type <tt>service-desc</tt>,<tt>service-doc</tt>, <tt>service-meta</tt>, or <tt>data-meta</tt>.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">14</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Consider your security needs</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">While not mandated, use of HTTPS vs. HTTP is encouraged throughout this standard.<br/>
Authenitcation is not precluded by this standard, but in keeping with guideline #1, this standard does not presume to dictate what authentication methods can be used.<br/>
API-Common — Core only defines GET requests. The security issues associated with CRUD are not applicable to this standard.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">15</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>API description</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The API definition is avaliable using the <tt>service-desc</tt> (machine readable) and <tt>service-doc</tt> (human readable) associations from the landing page.<br/>
OpenAPI is the only API definition type currently supported.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">16</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Use well-known identifiers</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">IANA identifiers are used where they are available. Where no IANA identifiers are appropriate, OGC registered identifiers are used.<br/>
OGC identifiers are only used after they have been reviewed and approved by the OGC Naming Authority.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">17</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Use explicit relations</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">All relations in this standard are typed using relation types registered in the IANA or the OGC relation type registers.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">18</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Support W3C cross-origin resource sharing</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">This guideline is addressed in <xref target="cross-origin-section"/>.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">19</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Resource encodings</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Conformance classes for both HTML and JSON have been defined. Implementation of both the HTML and JSON Conformance Classes is recommended.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">20</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Good APIs are testable from the beginning</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">The Abstract Test Suite (ATS) for this standard is provided in Annex A.<br/>
The ATS is defined to sufficient level of detail to validate that it is implementable and comprehensive</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">21</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Specify whether operations are safe and/or idempotent</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">According to IETF <eref type="inline" bibitemid="rfc7231" citeas="RFC 7231">RFC 7231</eref> “the GET, HEAD, OPTIONS, and TRACE methods are defined to be safe.” and the “PUT, DELETE, and safe request methods are idempotent”. All request methods in this standard (GET) are both safe and idempotent.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">22</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Make resources discoverable</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">All resouces defined in this standard can be navigated to through resource links and optional standard paths. All resource links are typed using registered relation types. These links are encoded using a standard link structure that includes the media type, language, and title of the resource.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="center">23</td>
<td valign="middle" align="center"><strong>Make default behavior explicit</strong></td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">This Standard defines the proper and allowed responses for any valid or invalid request.</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
</annex><annex id="_revision_history" obligation="informative">
<title>Revision History</title>
<table id="revision-history"><colgroup><col width="12%"/><col width="18%"/><col width="12%"/><col width="12%"/><col width="46%"/></colgroup>
<name>Revision History</name>
<thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left">Date</th>
<th valign="middle" align="left">Release</th>
<th valign="middle" align="left">Editor</th>
<th valign="middle" align="left">Primary clauses modified</th>
<th valign="middle" align="left">Description</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">2019-10-31</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">October 2019 snapshot</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">C. Heazel</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">all</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Baseline update</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">2020-04-21</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Public Comments</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">C. Heazel</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">all</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Separation of Collections from Core plus additional comment adjudications.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">2021-04-12</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Public Comments</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">C. Heazel</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">all</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Second public comment period.</td>
</tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">2021-08-01</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Final Review</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">C. Heazel</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">all</td>
<td valign="middle" align="left">Ready for SWG review and TC vote</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
</annex><bibliography><references id="_references" normative="true" obligation="informative">
<title>Normative references</title><p id="_307b20e2-9e40-db56-abbf-2822ab2941cc">The following documents are referred to in the text in such a way that some or all of their content constitutes requirements of this document. For dated references, only the edition cited applies. For undated references, the latest edition of the referenced document (including any amendments) applies.</p>
 <bibitem id="rfc2818" type="standard">  <fetched>2022-07-29</fetched>  
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">HTTP Over TLS</title>
  <uri type="xml">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaton/relaton-data-ietf/master/data/reference.RFC.2818.xml</uri>  <uri type="src">https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2818</uri>  <docidentifier type="RFC" primary="true">RFC 2818</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="RFC" scope="anchor">RFC2818</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="DOI">10.17487/RFC2818</docidentifier>  <docnumber>RFC2818</docnumber>  <date type="published">    <on>2000-05</on>  </date>  <contributor>    <role type="publisher"/>    <organization>      
<name>Internet Engineering Task Force</name>
      <abbreviation>IETF</abbreviation>    </organization>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">E. Rescorla</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <language>en</language>  <script>Latn</script>  <abstract format="text/html" language="en" script="Latn">    <p id="_b44521d2-31f1-5460-f2ca-64ddda4d1e4e">This memo describes how to use Transport Layer Security (TLS) to secure Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) connections over the Internet. This memo provides information for the Internet community.</p>
  </abstract>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">RFC</title>
    <number>2818</number>  </series></bibitem>
 <bibitem id="rfc3986" type="standard">  <fetched>2022-07-29</fetched>  
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
  <uri type="xml">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaton/relaton-data-ietf/master/data/reference.RFC.3986.xml</uri>  <uri type="src">https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3986</uri>  <docidentifier type="RFC" primary="true">RFC 3986</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="RFC" scope="anchor">RFC3986</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="DOI">10.17487/RFC3986</docidentifier>  <docnumber>RFC3986</docnumber>  <date type="published">    <on>2005-01</on>  </date>  <contributor>    <role type="publisher"/>    <organization>      
<name>Internet Engineering Task Force</name>
      <abbreviation>IETF</abbreviation>    </organization>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">T. Berners-Lee</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">R. Fielding</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">L. Masinter</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <language>en</language>  <script>Latn</script>  <abstract format="text/html" language="en" script="Latn">    <p id="_f52cba5d-c9d1-602c-4e9a-858f49f8dbec">A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters that identifies an abstract or physical resource. This specification defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet. The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs, allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every possible identifier. This specification does not define a generative grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual specifications of each URI scheme. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</p>
  </abstract>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">STD</title>
    <number>66</number>  </series>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">RFC</title>
    <number>3986</number>  </series></bibitem>
 <bibitem id="rfc6570" type="standard">  <fetched>2022-07-29</fetched>  
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">URI Template</title>
  <uri type="xml">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaton/relaton-data-ietf/master/data/reference.RFC.6570.xml</uri>  <uri type="src">https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6570</uri>  <docidentifier type="RFC" primary="true">RFC 6570</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="RFC" scope="anchor">RFC6570</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="DOI">10.17487/RFC6570</docidentifier>  <docnumber>RFC6570</docnumber>  <date type="published">    <on>2012-03</on>  </date>  <contributor>    <role type="publisher"/>    <organization>      
<name>Internet Engineering Task Force</name>
      <abbreviation>IETF</abbreviation>    </organization>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">J. Gregorio</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">R. Fielding</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">M. Hadley</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">M. Nottingham</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">D. Orchard</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <language>en</language>  <script>Latn</script>  <abstract format="text/html" language="en" script="Latn">    <p id="_6d8beb60-0f5e-a5bf-b247-a018d1fb6454">A URI Template is a compact sequence of characters for describing a range of Uniform Resource Identifiers through variable expansion. This specification defines the URI Template syntax and the process for expanding a URI Template into a URI reference, along with guidelines for the use of URI Templates on the Internet. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</p>
  </abstract>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">RFC</title>
    <number>6570</number>  </series></bibitem>
 <bibitem id="rfc7231" type="standard">  <fetched>2022-07-29</fetched>  
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Semantics and Content</title>
  <uri type="xml">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaton/relaton-data-ietf/master/data/reference.RFC.7231.xml</uri>  <uri type="src">https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7231</uri>  <docidentifier type="RFC" primary="true">RFC 7231</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="RFC" scope="anchor">RFC7231</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="DOI">10.17487/RFC7231</docidentifier>  <docnumber>RFC7231</docnumber>  <date type="published">    <on>2014-06</on>  </date>  <contributor>    <role type="publisher"/>    <organization>      
<name>Internet Engineering Task Force</name>
      <abbreviation>IETF</abbreviation>    </organization>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="editor"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">R. Fielding</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="editor"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">J. Reschke</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <language>en</language>  <script>Latn</script>  <abstract format="text/html" language="en" script="Latn">    <p id="_45d82e59-7f2f-702e-7573-46773039349f">The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless \%application- level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems. This document defines the semantics of HTTP/1.1 messages, as expressed by request methods, request header fields, response status codes, and response header fields, along with the payload of messages (metadata and body content) and mechanisms for content negotiation.</p>
  </abstract>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">RFC</title>
    <number>7231</number>  </series></bibitem>
 <bibitem id="rfc7232" type="standard">  <fetched>2022-07-29</fetched>  
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Conditional Requests</title>
  <uri type="xml">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaton/relaton-data-ietf/master/data/reference.RFC.7232.xml</uri>  <uri type="src">https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7232</uri>  <docidentifier type="RFC" primary="true">RFC 7232</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="RFC" scope="anchor">RFC7232</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="DOI">10.17487/RFC7232</docidentifier>  <docnumber>RFC7232</docnumber>  <date type="published">    <on>2014-06</on>  </date>  <contributor>    <role type="publisher"/>    <organization>      
<name>Internet Engineering Task Force</name>
      <abbreviation>IETF</abbreviation>    </organization>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="editor"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">R. Fielding</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="editor"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">J. Reschke</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <language>en</language>  <script>Latn</script>  <abstract format="text/html" language="en" script="Latn">    <p id="_0dda6277-9907-73d7-0b31-81611064751f">The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless application- level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems. This document defines HTTP/1.1 conditional requests, including metadata header fields for indicating state changes, request header fields for making preconditions on such state, and rules for constructing the responses to a conditional request when one or more preconditions evaluate to false.</p>
  </abstract>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">RFC</title>
    <number>7232</number>  </series></bibitem>
 <bibitem id="rfc7807" type="standard">  <fetched>2022-07-29</fetched>  
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Problem Details for HTTP APIs</title>
  <uri type="xml">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaton/relaton-data-ietf/master/data/reference.RFC.7807.xml</uri>  <uri type="src">https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7807</uri>  <docidentifier type="RFC" primary="true">RFC 7807</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="RFC" scope="anchor">RFC7807</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="DOI">10.17487/RFC7807</docidentifier>  <docnumber>RFC7807</docnumber>  <date type="published">    <on>2016-03</on>  </date>  <contributor>    <role type="publisher"/>    <organization>      
<name>Internet Engineering Task Force</name>
      <abbreviation>IETF</abbreviation>    </organization>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">M. Nottingham</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">E. Wilde</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <language>en</language>  <script>Latn</script>  <abstract format="text/html" language="en" script="Latn">    <p id="_b5e06edf-a300-faf3-7c95-0d4fe34fb6f9">This document defines a “problem detail” as a way to carry machine- readable details of errors in a HTTP response to avoid the need to define new error response formats for HTTP APIs.</p>
  </abstract>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">RFC</title>
    <number>7807</number>  </series></bibitem>
 <bibitem id="rfc8288" type="standard">  <fetched>2022-07-29</fetched>  
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Web Linking</title>
  <uri type="xml">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaton/relaton-data-ietf/master/data/reference.RFC.8288.xml</uri>  <uri type="src">https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8288</uri>  <docidentifier type="RFC" primary="true">RFC 8288</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="RFC" scope="anchor">RFC8288</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="DOI">10.17487/RFC8288</docidentifier>  <docnumber>RFC8288</docnumber>  <date type="published">    <on>2017-10</on>  </date>  <contributor>    <role type="publisher"/>    <organization>      
<name>Internet Engineering Task Force</name>
      <abbreviation>IETF</abbreviation>    </organization>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="author"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">M. Nottingham</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <language>en</language>  <script>Latn</script>  <abstract format="text/html" language="en" script="Latn">    <p id="_f78305d7-1132-e2f9-b878-033e62ac07bd">This specification defines a model for the relationships between resources on the Web (“links”) and the type of those relationships (“link relation types”).</p>
    <p id="_e69c24ff-ecb9-f9d8-9e89-6ce80b87b085">It also defines the serialisation of such links in HTTP headers with the Link header field.</p>
  </abstract>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">RFC</title>
    <number>8288</number>  </series></bibitem>
 <bibitem id="rfc8259" type="standard">  <fetched>2022-07-29</fetched>  
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">The JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) Data Interchange Format</title>
  <uri type="xml">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaton/relaton-data-ietf/master/data/reference.RFC.8259.xml</uri>  <uri type="src">https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8259</uri>  <docidentifier type="RFC" primary="true">RFC 8259</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="RFC" scope="anchor">RFC8259</docidentifier>  <docidentifier type="DOI">10.17487/RFC8259</docidentifier>  <docnumber>RFC8259</docnumber>  <date type="published">    <on>2017-12</on>  </date>  <contributor>    <role type="publisher"/>    <organization>      
<name>Internet Engineering Task Force</name>
      <abbreviation>IETF</abbreviation>    </organization>  </contributor>  <contributor>    <role type="editor"/>    <person>      
<name>        <completename language="en">T. Bray</completename>      </name>
    </person>  </contributor>  <language>en</language>  <script>Latn</script>  <abstract format="text/html" language="en" script="Latn">    <p id="_09077869-25be-38e2-f3d2-00b84ccfd798">JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) is a lightweight, text-based, language-independent data interchange format. It was derived from the ECMAScript Programming Language Standard. JSON defines a small set of formatting rules for the portable representation of structured data.</p>
    <p id="_06ea85d8-9442-d390-9040-3aca84105272">This document removes inconsistencies with other specifications of JSON, repairs specification errors, and offers experience-based interoperability guidance.</p>
  </abstract>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">STD</title>
    <number>90</number>  </series>  <series type="main">    
<title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">RFC</title>
    <number>8259</number>  </series></bibitem>
<bibitem id="openapi"><formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Open API Initiative: <strong>OpenAPI Specification</strong>, Version 3.0. The latest patch version at the time of publication of this standard was 3.0.3, available from <link target="http://spec.openapis.org/oas/v3.0.3"/>.</formattedref><docidentifier>openapi</docidentifier></bibitem>
</references><references id="Bibliography" normative="false" obligation="informative">
<title>Bibliography</title><bibitem id="fielding2000">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Fielding, Roy Thomas: <strong>Architectural Styles and the Design of Network-based Software Architectures</strong>. Doctoral dissertation, University of California, Irvine, 2000, <link target="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~fielding/pubs/dissertation/fielding_dissertation.pdf">https://www.ics.uci.edu/fielding/pubs/dissertation/fielding_dissertation.pdf</link></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[1]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="k-and-r-1978">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Kernighan, B., Richie, D.: <strong>The C Programming Language</strong>, Bell Laboratories, 1978</formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[2]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="link-relations">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">IANA: <strong>Link Relation Types</strong>, <link target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/link-relations/link-relations.xml"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[3]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="rfc7230">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Fielding, R., Reschke, J.: <strong>IETF RFC 7230, Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Message Syntax and Routing</strong>, <link target="https://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rfc7230.txt"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[4]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="rfc7235">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Fielding, R., Reschke, J.: <strong>IETF RFC 7235, Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Authentication</strong>, <link target="https://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rfc7235.txt"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[5]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="rfc7538">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Reschke, J.: <strong>IETF RFC 7538, The Hypertext Transfer Protocol Status Code 308 (Permanent Redirect)</strong>, <link target="https://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rfc7538.txt"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[6]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="iso15836-2">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">ISO 15836-2:2019, <strong>Information and documentation — The Dublin Core metadata element set — Part 2: DCMI Properties and classes</strong></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[7]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="jschema">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">json-schema-org: <strong>JSON Schema,</strong> September 2019, <link target="https://json-schema.org/specification.html"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[8]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="bnf-citation">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">ISO/IEC 14977:1996(E) <strong>Information technology – Syntactic metalanguage – Extended BNF</strong>, available from <link target="https://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/s026153_ISO_IEC_14977_1996(E).zip">ISO</link>.</formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[9]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="ogc-06-121">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Whiteside, A., Greenwood, J.: <strong>OGC Web Services Common Standard</strong>, version 2.0, <link target="http://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=38867">OGC 06-121r9</link></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[10]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="ogc08-131">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Open Geospatial Consortium: <strong>The Specification Model — A Standard for Modular specifications</strong>, <link target="https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=34762">OGC 08-131</link></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[11]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="schema_org">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">Schema.org: <link target="http://schema.org/docs/schemas.html"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[12]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="WEBARCH">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">W3C: <strong>Architecture of the World Wide Web, Volume One</strong>, W3C Recommendation, 15 December 2004, <link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[13]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="DCAT">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">W3C: <strong>Data Catalog Vocabulary (DCAT) — Version 2</strong>, W3C Recommendation, 04 February 2020, <link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/vocab-dcat-2/"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[14]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="DWBP">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">W3C: <strong>Data on the Web Best Practices</strong>, W3C Recommendation, 31 January 2017, <link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/dwbp/"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[15]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="SDWBP">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">W3C/OGC: <strong>Spatial Data on the Web Best Practices</strong>, W3C Working Group Note, 28 September 2017, <link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/sdw-bp/"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[16]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="html5">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">W3C: <strong>HTML5, W3C Recommendation</strong>, <link target="http://www.w3.org/TR/html5/"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[17]</docidentifier>
</bibitem><bibitem id="xmlschema-part2">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml">W3C Recommendation: <strong>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second Edition</strong>, 28 October 2004, <link target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/"/></formattedref>
  <docidentifier type="metanorma">[18]</docidentifier>
</bibitem>


















</references></bibliography>
</ogc-standard>
